<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Postilion. Or a new almanacke and astrologicke, prophetical, prognostication. Calculated for the whole world, and all creatures, and what the issue or event will be of the English warres, and of the Roman Empire, and that aboundance of calamities is yet to come, but after that an eternall peace, and a new world, and that unheard of and never knowne wonders will be, and what will happen from henceforth untill Christs comming, and herein is also sett downe a nativity, and prognostication for every particular man. / Written in High Dutch by Paulus Felghenore, and now translated into English, in the yeare 1655.</title>
            <author>Felgenhauer, Paul.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75074</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865758</idno>
  <idno type="VID">118009</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240911793</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E860_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206639</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865758</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865758e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118009)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E860[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Postilion. Or a new almanacke and astrologicke, prophetical, prognostication. Calculated for the whole world, and all creatures, and what the issue or event will be of the English warres, and of the Roman Empire, and that aboundance of calamities is yet to come, but after that an eternall peace, and a new world, and that unheard of and never knowne wonders will be, and what will happen from henceforth untill Christs comming, and herein is also sett downe a nativity, and prognostication for every particular man. / Written in High Dutch by Paulus Felghenore, and now translated into English, in the yeare 1655.</title>
                  <author>Felgenhauer, Paul.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for H: Crips and Lodo: Lloyd, and are to be sold at their shops next to the Castle in Cornhill, and in Popes-head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of the Dutch original.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novemb: 17"; the first "English" has been marked out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Almanacs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118009:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118009:1"/>
            <p>Postilion, <hi>Or a New</hi> ALMANACKE <hi>AND</hi> Astrologicke, prophetical, Prognostication. <hi>Calculated for the whole World, and all</hi> Creatures, and what the Issue or Event will be of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Warres, and of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and that aboundance of Calamities is yet to come, but after that an Eternall Peace, and a New world, and that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of and never knowne wonders will be, and what <hi>will happen from henceforth untill Christs comming, and herein is also sett downe a Nativity, and Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nostication for every particular Man.</hi> Written in High Dutch by <hi>Paulus Felghenore,</hi> And now translated into <hi>English,</hi> in the yeare 1655.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Acts 3. 19, 20, 21.</bibl>
               <p>Repent yee therefore, and be converted, that your sinnes may be blotted out when the Times of refreshing shall come from the presence of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And he shall send Jesus Christ, which before was preached unto you.</p>
               <p>Whom the Heavens must Receive untill the Time of Restitution of all things which God hath spoken through the Mouth of all his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets since the World beganne.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>H: Crips</hi> and <hi>Lodo: Lloyd,</hi> and are to be sold at their Shops next to the <hi>Castle</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and in <hi>Popes</hi>-head Alley. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118009:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118009:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Epistle Dedicatory.</hi> TO M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>JACOB THYSIƲS,</hi> a singular lover of Divine, and Naturall Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as also of the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> and <hi>Astrology,</hi> and <hi>Geometry.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Deare Friend in Christ.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved Friend in the Lord; I wish to you and your loving ones from God abundance of grace and peace from Christ Jesus, and an enlightning of the Holy Ghost; the Apostle exhorts his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and us, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 14. Thus, <hi>Follow after Charity, and desire spirituall gifts, but the rather that yee may prophesie, for he that prophesieth, speaketh unto men, to edification and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation and comfort;</hi> Here the Apostle holds forth unto us three things, which wee ought to consider well; The first is <hi>Charity,</hi> in which wherewith and through which our Faith and Religion is justifyed, approved, and confirmed, and therefore where no Charity is, there the boasting and crying up of true Faith, and Religion is in vaine, and all knowledge, and whatsoever else may be is in vaine and of no use without Charity, as the Apostle speaketh plainly, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 13. Now wee very well know that there is great disputing and arguing about Faith and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, amongst those which are taught of God, and can conclude or determine nothing therein, the Reason is
<pb facs="tcp:118009:3"/> because they neither have nor know Charity, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew the onely summe of Religion and true Faith in God which is Love, and Charity, of which we read in <hi>Math. 22. 37, 38, 39. Deut.</hi> 6. 5. in the 1 <hi>Timothy</hi> 1. 5. None is knowne of God, but he that loves God, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 8. 3. and his Brother and Neighbour. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 11. 14. Therefore wee conclude of all men in the whole world, and of all their Beleivers, Religion and Gods worship, <hi>Chap. 4. ver:</hi> 7, 8. and Love is of God, <hi>and every one that loveth is borne of God, and knoweth God, but he that loveth not, knows not God, for God is love;</hi> and in his third Epistle, about the 11 <hi>v:</hi> sayth <hi>John, He that doth good is of God, but he that does evill does not see God,</hi> therefore this is the Conclusion of all men among all the Nations of the Earth, as the Holy Scripture speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>John 5. 39. Those that have done good shall rise unto Life, and those that have done evill shall rise unto Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Therefore whatever man soweth, he shall reape also, whether it be good or bad; Therefore let us doe good, and not to be weary of it;</hi> Galat: 5. 8, 9, 10. Wherefore thus wee conclude of all mens Faith and Religion; <hi>That whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver feareth God in what Nation soever and worketh righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, he is acceptable unto God,</hi> Act. 10. 35. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let no man erre and be deceived through an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and dead Faith; for none is justifyed of God, and to be able to enter into the kingdome of God, but he that worketh righteousnesse and doth the will of God, <hi>Math: 2. 21. 1 Joh. 3. 7, 8, 9, 10. It is he which shall abide for ever,</hi> Chap: 2. 17. <hi>and dwell on the holy Hill of the Lord,</hi> Psal. 15. <hi>and dwell on high,</hi> that is in heaven, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 33. 14, 15, 16. This now is the first thing the Apostle exhorts us unto, (to wit) Love, thereby is our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Beliefe knowne, what he is, and what he hath to expect, <hi>Rom:</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he exhorts us also that wee should strive
<pb facs="tcp:118009:3"/> about spirituall things, or spirituall Gifts, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour after them, the Reason why the Apostle admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth us unto them is, that we might grow rich in God through spirituall Gifts, in all manner of spirituall wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and understanding, and knowledge in the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of God the Father, and of Christ, 1 <hi>Corinth: 12. Ephes:</hi> 3. 16, 17, 18, 19. that our eyes may be enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through the Spirit of Wisdome and of the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the knowledge of God, <hi>Ephes:</hi> 1. 17, 18. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. 13. that wee should not allwayes continue to be such children, that are driven by every winde of Doctrine, by the slight and cunning craftinesse of men, <hi>ver:</hi> 14, 15. but that wee might attaine unto the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Saints, and of those that are perfect, which lye hid in the Mystery, of which, worldly men know nothing, nay it is hidd from the witty and wise men of this world; <hi>Math: 11. 25. Job 28. Wisdom 7. 10. 1 Corin:</hi> 2. 7, 8, 9, 10. Thus wee should strive after spirituall Gifts, that wee may learne to know the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of God, <hi>Colos: 2. 2. and that all the treasures of Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge are hidden in Christ,</hi> ver: 3. in regard of that knowledge all other things are accounted but Dung and double losse, <hi>Philip:</hi> 3. 7, 8. Thus shall wee be rich in God, and perfect, enriching others also; Thus the <hi>Corinthians</hi> according to the exhortation of the Apostle, who strove after Spirituall Gifts, and prayed to God for his Holy Spirit, and they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenished with all manner of spirituall Gifts; for when they assembled together in the Congregation every one made shew of his Gifts to the praise of God and to the edifying of the Congregation, as it plainly appears, 1 <hi>Corin:</hi> 14. But where are now adayes such Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations and spirituall Gifts? Are wee not rather deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by those which have not the Spirit? when we are zealous about the Spirit, and spirituall Gifts, and doe
<pb facs="tcp:118009:4"/> accuse us of seven and eight Devills, and that we have a familiar spirit; Nay it is so, but the Lord commeth and will judge it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Apostle admonisheth us to endeavour after prophesying, and 1 <hi>Thess:</hi> 5. 19, 20. he sayth, <hi>Quench not the Spirit, despise not prophesying;</hi> the <hi>Quaere</hi> here now is, what signifyes properly to prophesie, and what is the spirit of prophesying? Answer; These are the Prophets, which have the Spirit of the Testimony of Jesus Christ, <hi>Revel: 12. 17. Chap:</hi> 19. 10. Then wee aske what is the Testimony of Jesus Christ? Answer; This is the Testimony of Jesus Christ, and the Spirit of prophesying, That Jesus Christ is the Sonne of the living God, and the true God himselfe, and not a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as <hi>Adam</hi> was, and all are; <hi>Math. 16. 13. 16. 1 Joh.</hi> 5. 15. 10, 11. 12. 20. And thereby wee know that wee have the Spirit of prophesying, and the Testimony of Jesus Christ, if wee speake of Christ divinely, and not humanely, <hi>Math:</hi> 16. 23. if we speake the words of God and not of Men, thereby wee know that wee are of God and are sent of him; <hi>Joh. 3. 34. 1 John 4. 5, 6. 1 Peter</hi> 4. 11. Therefore the Spirit of prophesying, hath the true Doctrine, and Testimony of Jesus Christ, for he speaketh divinely, and with such words which the Holy Ghost teacheth, and not the spirit of this world, which teacheth words of humane wisdome, and not words of God; 1 <hi>Corinth: 2. 12. Chap:</hi> 2. 12, 13. Now through the spirituall Doctrine the Congregation of God is builded on the spirituall Rocke, and foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is Christ; <hi>Chap: 10. 4. Ephes:</hi> 2. 20. On which Foundation and Rocke, our most holy Faith is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as on God himselfe, and not on any Creature.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Congregation is admonished and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted by prophesying, 1 <hi>Corinth:</hi> 14 3. and meliora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>ver:</hi> 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>, that shee in her wisdome should take heed
<pb facs="tcp:118009:4"/> of such who are earthly minded, for through the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of errours the Congregations are scattered, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainly by all humane sects, the Reason is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the false Prophets deny Christ, and with forged words worke on men, and have not the Testimony of God and of Christ, nor the spirit of prophesying, but the spirit of this world, in a Wisdome which is from below; <hi>James</hi> 3. 15. according to the Flesh, which is in enmity against God; <hi>Rom:</hi> 8. 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and lastly, wee are through the Spirit of prophesying comforted in that which is to come, Namely, that wee shall be redeemed from this world, and from all miseries, therefore the Spirit of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing foretells us of future things, for our comfort, that wee may keepe faith in Patience, and be circumspect, and long with the whole Creature, after our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on which wee waite and depend; <hi>Rom:</hi> 8. 21, 22, 23. Thereupon the Prophesie foretells us of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and of the end of this world, with the extirpation and destruction of all the wicked, and of the true peace, and eternall Joy, as also of the great Glory in the future World of the kingdome of God, of which wee comfort one another, and rejoyce in that which is to come.</p>
            <p>Now such a thing, namely, that which is to come, is foretold also in the Treatise called <hi>Postilion,</hi> through the Gift of Prophesing, though this our Prophesing, be not so perfect, yet, he who is spirituall, and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the Congregation of the Lord, will not despise it, but remember what the Apostle sayth, 1 <hi>Corin: 13. 9. That our prophesing is but in part.</hi> But the Reason why I dedicated this Treatise to my Loving Friend, and published the same in his Name, because he is a Lover of the Divine, and Naturall Wisdome, and searcheth after Truth, in one or other, and waiteth
<pb facs="tcp:118009:5"/> with me and all true beleivers, and with the whole Creature, upon the Generall Redemption neere at hand as possibly may be credited; Therefore my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and purpose is to bring in this Booke this glad tydings, and sure Newes; First to all the select belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, then to the whole people of <hi>Israel,</hi> and <hi>Juda,</hi> and at the last to Heaven and Earth, and all the Creatures therein, especially seeing a good Message is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and I make no doubt but it will be so received, (as it is intended) first by you, who is my Deare Friend in Christ; next by the Christians and Jewes, and at last of the Spirit of all the Creatures, who with me joyntly expect their Redemption, for which God the Creator of all things make us fit and worthy; whose Name be praised for ever, to whose Grace wee recommend our selves.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Loving Friend, and Servant. <hi>Postilion.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Dated at <hi>Amsterdam</hi>
                  <date>the 15<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>January, Stilo Novo.</hi> 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118009:5"/>
            <head>A Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous and loving Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is almost Naturall to Man, that he is desirous to heare Newes, in case he be not deceived, and endamaged thereby, as our first Mother <hi>Eve,</hi> who hearkned to the Serpent, who by the seducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of of the Devill, told to her Newes also, whereby shee was so much deceived, that not onely <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and all wee with them, but Heaven and Earth also, and all what therein is, are fallen into great Necessity, Death and Misery, and continue still therein even till now; whereas it is meete for a Watchman which standeth on the Guard Day &amp; Night to be faithfull and diligent in his Office, and to tell of that which he seeth comming a farre off, that with a good Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he may say before God as it is written in the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> Chap: 21. 8. <hi>My Lord I stand continually upon the Watch Tower in the day time, and I am sett in my Ward whole Nights;</hi> Therefore I thought it fit to make mention and give notice of, and withall to commend my Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that I may not stand ashamed at the Lords comming.</p>
            <p>Whereas, many things have been foretold hitherto of Peace, so that all men wished and longed after it, yet the Watch man on the Tower of the Lord sayth thus; 1 <hi>Thes. 5. 3. For when they shall say peace and safety, then sudden Destruction commeth on them, as Travaile upon a Woman with Childe, aad they shall not escape;</hi> Therefore I speake to you of the sword, and not of Peace, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeing the sword comming on my Tower, and truely I have declared it many yeares agoe, and have been taxed for it hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily, and I must thinke of an Answer to him that Rebuked
<pb facs="tcp:118009:6"/> for it; Now the Lord sayth thus, <hi>Write the vision, and paynt it on a Table, that the passers by, may read it;</hi> Thus, The Prophesie shall be yet in due time accomplished, and will at the last fully come to passe, even to the Day, and will not tarry, and though it tarrys waite thou neverthelesse, for it will assuredly come, and that not long; But he that is obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, shall finde no Rest in his Heart, <hi>for the Just liveth by Faith:</hi> Because I see the sword comming, therefore I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne you of it, and that indeed a Triple sword, over the three States of the World, as you will Read anon in this our <hi>Almanacke</hi> and <hi>Prognostication;</hi> therefore doe not take it ill but consider what is written; <hi>Ezek: 33.</hi> and that you may not fall into Tymorousnesse and dispaire, I foretell you also of a Peace, but of such a Peace, which men doe not make, but of such a one which the Lord God will make, as you shall heare afterwards, and that Peace will last firmely for ever, and shall never be broken againe; <hi>Psal: 72. Isai: 9. 7.</hi> Now that every one may know, as it were in a short Compendium, what the Newes is which I am to declare to all? To it I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, that it is this, That not onely wee Men, but also Heaven and Earth, and all what therein is shall be renewed, and all the Calamities which have befallen us and all the Creatures by reason of sinne, and have lasted now these 6000 yeares, shall be taken wholly away at once, and all shall be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to such a good state and glory, as it was before the fall of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and this will come to passe at the Glorious and joyfull comming of our Lord Jesus Christ, by such a means, that the Tree of Life shall and must be broken, through which breaking all shall come to right and good againe, even as by the breaking of the former Tree, and by the enjoyng of its fruite, all is come into evill and Death; This is the joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Tydings which wee tell unto you, in the Name of the Lord who hath sent me; Now he that beleiveth it, and repenteth truely, desisting from evill, and doing Good, and calleth on the Name of the Lord, he shall not onely see and enjoy that
<pb facs="tcp:118009:6"/> Newes which wee tell you of, but will be delivered also from all Mischiefe and Misery; as it is written, <hi>Psal: 27. 13, 14. Joel 2. 32.</hi> And this now is the seale of God, whereby are knowne those that belong to God, namely, Faith, Love, and Hope in the Holy Ghost, He that hath this Seale, him the Lord knoweth, and it is he who knows, and is knowne of the Lord, <hi>2 Tim: 2. 19. 1 John 2. 3, 4, 5, 6. 1 Corinth: 8. 3.</hi> Such a one who hath this Seale and maketh shew of it in True Repentance, and in a godly Life and conversation before God and Man, shall not be touched by the sword, and the Destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Angel, according to the promise in <hi>Ezekiel 9. 4, 5, 6. Apocalyps 7. 3.</hi> But he that hath not this Seale in his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, which Forehead, is his dayly life and conversation, he will be touched and destroyed by the sword, and by the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>custs, and by the foure Destroying Angells, though he were a Prophet, even as <hi>Bileam</hi> was, <hi>Revel: 9. 4. Numb. 31. 8.</hi> But to speake in one word what the Seale of God is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Children of God are sealed, viz. the holy Spirit of God and of Christ, whereby wee know the Children of God; but he that hath not this Seale, and this Spirit, he is not the Child of God, <hi>Rom: 8. 9. 15. 2 Corinth: 1. 21. 22. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes: 1. 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas Astrologers and Almanackmakers, usually calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Nativities for Men, touching their Fortunes, therefore wee intend to doe the like, so that every man be he of what state and condition soever, hath his Nativity hereby sett in the aforesaid Seale, according to which he may undoubtedly and assuredly regulate his life, as in one word for the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but concerning the particulars, they shall follow in order in our sequent Almanacke and Prognostication, and in that manner, that every one shall admire; the Reason whereof is this, because some Newes is told, which formerly other Ages have not heard of, as it is written, <hi>Isaiah 48. 6, 7.</hi> Which newes, or new thing is this, namely, that all shall be renewed, and the Tree of Life shall be broken, and its fruit shall be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:118009:7"/> and enjoyed, and all things shall be ordered and regulated in so good away, as it was before the fall, and the whole Creature shall be delivered from Vanity and Misery; <hi>Acts 3. 20, 21. Dan: 9. 24. Rom: 8. 21. Isaiah 65. 17. 25. Chap: 11. 6. 2 Peter 3. 13. Psal: 102. 27: Heb: 12. 27.</hi> Now of this joyfull Newes never any Astrologer or Almanack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker hath written, the reason of it was, bocause the Booke of Heaven was sealed from them hitherto as all other Bookes; <hi>Isaiah 29. 10, 11, 12.</hi> and God mocketh them, <hi>Chap: 47. 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</hi> and know not that <hi>Babylon</hi> shall fall and suddenly be Ruined; and indeed I have often wondered, that not any of them should ever have made mention of it, and that all the Almanackmakers and Astrologers, should be so ignorant and starke blind, that they could not take notice of the Transcendently great alterations over Heaven and Earth, and over the whole World; but truely the Cause is this, that they have not studied nor learned their Astrology out of the holy Scripture, and know not this one thing, whether the Sunne, or the Earth stands still, or which part is in its Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution? Is it not a sinne, and shame? Now if the true Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers will rightly view and consider the booke of Heaven, then they will finde wonders upon wonders, to which this our New Almanacke and Prognostication will minister sufficient occasion, for the Time is come that all bookes shall be opened which hitherto have been sealed; Because that Time is come, in which this World shall be sealed, and a New World shall be Revealed, as wee have declared unto you, and hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied of, 4 of <hi>Esdras 6. 20.</hi> Therefore wee will not hold forth unto you this our New Almanacke and Astrologicall Prognostication without the holy Scripture, but rather whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of it, except what perticular Conjectures shall be inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, so that the Reader himselfe may peruse the booke of the Lord with those of <hi>Berroha,</hi> and search therein whether the things be so as S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Paul</hi> hath told them, <hi>Isa: 34. 16. Acts 17. 11.</hi> Wherefore least any one should be deceived, for the holy
<pb facs="tcp:118009:7"/> Scripture is as full of Mysteries as the Firmament is full of Starres, he that can Read therein to whom they stand open, and hath received of the Angel, with <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> the Booke opened, little or nothing will be concealed from him but he will be able to prophesie to the Gentils and Nations, and to many Kings, <hi>Revel: 10, 9, 10. 11. Ezek: 3. 3.</hi> Now of this Prophesing you shall heare all along in this Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nostication, the Father of Lights, from whom all good Gifts come from above, who liberally distributeth his Gifts to all those, who aske of him for his Wisdome, will be pleased to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten us altogether, that our Darknesse, and our Lampe may be enlightened from above to behold the Light in his Light, to the praise and honour of his Name, and our salvation, Amen; <hi>Psal: 18. 29. 2 Sam. 22. 26, 27. Psal. 36. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written at <hi>Bederkesa;</hi>
                  <date>The 1<seg rend="sup">st</seg> of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prognostication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118009:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118009:8"/>
            <head>Postilion. <hi>Or a New</hi> ALMANACKE <hi>AND</hi> Astrologicke, prophetical, Prognostication.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The First Chapter. Of the Time, Age, and Yeare of the World, and what is the true Calculation thereof, which hitherto hath not been knowne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Holy Ghost by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us in this manner; <hi>Ephes: 5. 14. Awake thou that sleepest and arise from the Dead, and Christ shall give thee Light;</hi> ver: 15. <hi>See then yee walke circumspectly, not as Fooles but as Wise;</hi> ver: 16. <hi>Redeeming Time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the dayes are evill;</hi> ver: 17. <hi>Wherefore be yee not unwise, but understanding what the will of the Lord is,</hi> Rom: 12. 2. Whereas Almanackmakers sett the Time in the Frontispeice of their <hi>Almanacke,</hi> namely, the Yeare of the World, therefore wee will keepe the same order, and in the first Chapter, wee will speake of the Time, of the Age, and Yeares of the World in a just and right Chronologie out of the ground of the holy Scripture, and that for this Reason, because the Time runneth to an end, from whence wee shall know and observe, rejoycing and comforting our selves the more, because our Redemption draweth nigh.</p>
               <p>Now whereas the World was created of God in six dayes, and on the seventh day all was accomplished, <hi>then God rested the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118009:9"/> day</hi> &amp;c. Thereupon wee will conclude according to the Grace which God hath bestowed on us in the Spirit of prophesie, that the World shall also last six dayes, or six thousand Yeares, but the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Thousand Yeare will be the Sabboth and Rest in these thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of yeares, of which is plainly spoken in the <hi>Revelation.</hi> Now of this Sabboth you may read and exactly consider the Scripture, <hi>Heb:</hi> 3. and 4. <hi>Levit:</hi> 25. and make a diligent search what it may signifie, why God hath sanctified the Seaventh day, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the same to be kept holy; <hi>Exod: 20. 8. Deut.</hi> 5. 12. and what wee are to consider thereby, and that wee should not any longer continue in ignorance, but be understanding and rational, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Sabboth what it signifies, and intimates unto us, and not to looke upon it as a Cow on a New Gate (as the usual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe is.)</p>
               <p>Now as the World was created in six dayes, and that out of the water, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 5. through the Spirit, which moved on the water, who keepeth the water by his power in a Fluidnesse continually; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may perceive how the Fountaines arise and spring, because there is in the Water a Living Spirit, and a Stirring Winde, which driveth and moveth it, keeping it in a continual Fluer; Thus much intimateth unto us also the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea in its six houres Ebbing and six houres Flowing; the time of these six dayes and six thousand yeares, and the twelve houres in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> the twelve houres of the Master of the house, which now are counted as for one Day, <hi>Math:</hi> 20. Which Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea Water in its mystery shall of us be exactly viewed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered; and although hitherto none could finde out, or tell the true cause of this Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea Water; Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse, wee will reveale the same herewith unto you, Namely, the Spirit, through which the World was made out of the Water, the same is indeed in the Water with his Winde, which stirreth and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it; Now the Spirit is in both Poles, the Articke, and Antar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, out of his Transcendent Spheare, wherein he fullfilleth the whole Circumference of the World, <hi>Wisdom</hi> 1. 7 in a very little Center with all his fullnesse, as corporeally contracted, and concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated; and a True Magnett which attracteth the Waters which at the beginning of the Creation, were begotten out of the Winde and Spirit, and so respireth, or deduceth againe in six houres, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Number of the six Dayes, and twelve houres of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118009:9"/> Creation, and also of the Time of the World; Now this Spirit of the World dwells likewise bodily in the two Poles on which the World is firme, and hangeth thereon as on the Navel String, and so becomes the Navel of the World, where the whole world in the water floweth in and out, and wherein it dwelleth also with all its fullnesse, as in a Concenterated Center.</p>
               <p>Now this Spirit of the world dwelleth also in the despicable Magnett; This is the Reason why the Magnett continually poynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as it were with Fingers at the Pole, which doth teach and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate unto us, that the Spirit of the world dwelleth in the Pole, and that wee also ought to enquire and search after what it signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, attracting to us the Spirit from above, even as the Magnett drawes the Iron on the one side, and repercusseth to the other, which Mystery hitherto hath been concealed from those who in their clearest sight are blinde; And there is such a Mystery in the Water by Reason of the Spirit which is therein, that no man can beleive, namely, a Magnetick power to attract, and take away all Diseases, be they called what they will, if the mystery of the water were knowne; and least you should thinke I mocke, and tell Fables unto you, Then Remember the Fountaines which cure Diseases, and consider what is written, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5 10. &amp;c. <hi>John 5. 4. Chap:</hi> 9. 7. 11. And why Christ hath instituted the Baptisme with water, &amp;c. And he that hath an uncleane skinne, or hath any other soares, or Cresences, let him but wash himselfe with or in the Sea-water at the Decrease of the Moone when it ebbeth, he will be pure and healed of those uncleane Cresences, and then you will know the wonders of the waters, and consider of them better.</p>
               <p>In the Balticke Sea, there is neither Ebbing nor flowing, the Reason is, because it is not opposite to the Pole; But why these Mysteries have not been hitherto revealed; Is this the Reason, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause our Phylosophers know not the Principles, and Elements, and powers of the World, though there were never so many of them; Now there is not foure but seaven Elements and Powers of the World, Namely, Spirit, Aire, Water, Light, Heaven, and Earth: The water is the Center corporeally, and stands onely in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; But the Fire is no Element, but an opposite Element, of which more is spoken in our sphere of Wisdome, or Revelation of Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, wherein is found the key unto Wisdome &amp;c. But let no Man marvell; for the Time is come at last in which all things concealed shall be Revealed.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118009:10"/>
               <p>Now concerning the Yeares of the World, from <hi>Adam</hi> to the Deluge there are 1656 yeares; From <hi>Noah</hi> to Christ are 2574 yeares: Thus Christ is borne in the yeare of the world 4230; and wee write in 1646 yeare, the yeare of the world 5877. The ground of the Computation and Calculation, of the middle Joynt or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (to wit) the 2574 yeares wee take from the speech of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel unto <hi>Ezdras</hi> the Prophet out of the fourth Booke of <hi>Ezdras,</hi> in the 14 Chap: and the 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg> verse: These 12 parts you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, which beginne not from <hi>Adam,</hi> but from <hi>Noah</hi> for a directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to you; Christ was borne on the third Sabboth yeare of the 31 Jubile yeare, and was baptized by <hi>John</hi> in the 31 Jubile-yeare ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our thinking and conjecture; in the 30 yeare of his Age, and in the middle of the weeke (Namely) in the last and seaventh weeke of the 32 Jubile yeare, was <hi>Jerusalem</hi> destroyed, and the Sacrifice abolished according to the Prophesie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> Chap. 9. ver: 27.</p>
               <p>Now the 6000 yeares shall not be accomplished, but shall be shortned for the Elect sake; These abbreviated yeares wee leave to the omniscience of the Almighty; But those who have the Spirit of Wisdome, to them wee hold forth that which the Angel sayd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ezdras,</hi> the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Chap: 7<seg rend="sup">th</seg> ver: 28. 30. Inquire diligently into the Computation of those 400 yeares and 7 dayes, and you will finde them also in <hi>Ezdras,</hi> and then you will know the Mystery, and that which wee have mentioned in the Preface of the Sabboth. Furthermore, concerning the Time you must know that the Time of the abomination of Destruction will expire and come to an End in the 1290 dayes after 1600. And wee consider very well what the new Starre 1604, hath told and intimated to the Magi of the East, namely, the Nativity of the Childe of the woman, <hi>Revel:</hi> 12. of which in our Sermon preached on the Gospel on the Day of the apparition of Christ, and written on the last ended Moneth of March; The great Blazing Starre <hi>Anno</hi> 1618, hath sounded the Seaventh Trumpett for an Alarme to all the world, which you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not gainesay, and foretold the Ruine of all Kingdomes, and Kings of the Earth, and the Judgement over the World, and the comming of the Lord; Hitherto wee are in the 5<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Viol, which manifestly will shew it selfe in the yeare 1655, and that very powerfully; For you see how the kingdome of the Beast is darkened, and then the foure destroying Angells, which hitherto were bound shall be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118009:10"/> whose office and effect, read, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9. 14, 15. of whom this is our meaning and opinion, that they will hold and gather in the great Harvest, described, <hi>Revel:</hi> 14. and that the crooked Sickle, and the knife for cutting the Clusters, is the Turke, which will come with foure great and mighty Potentates to make a horrible slaughter, but presently after shall be destroyed, and in a way of prophesing I hold him to be the great River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> on which the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Viol is to be powred out, dryed up, and perish, for another People shall come into his Countrey, which goeth also through the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which shall be even dryed up; what manner of people this is Read <hi>Esdras</hi> 13. 40, &amp;c. For God will doe even the same Miracles which he did when <hi>Israel</hi> came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which read <hi>Isaiah 11. 15, 16 Chap: 24. 14. Chap: 27. 12, 13. Jerem: 31. 9. Micah</hi> 7. 15. This People of the Tenn Tribes of <hi>Israel</hi> shall come with their Kings from the East through <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates;</hi> Revel: 16 12. Which now dwelleth behinde the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dional Pole in the unknowne Land not knowne of us as yet, but shall be now found and knowne by the powring of the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Viol: We are fully of opinion that the Turke, will make a prey upon these two Partyes falling out and fighting one against another.</p>
               <p>Thus wee conclude the First Chapter of our Prognosticks, the event whereof Time will teach, in the meane while, let the well wishers and <hi>Daniel</hi> his Fellows read the 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg> and 12<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Chapters of the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Esdras,</hi> of the three headed Eagle, and consider of it, according to my conjecture the Turke will be the first that will perish.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The Second Chapter. Concerning the true, infallible, and assured signe of the End, whereby the End may be knowne.</head>
               <p>TO this <hi>Quaere</hi> Christ answereth most gratiously, <hi>Math:</hi> 24. 14. Where he setts downe some signes and prophesieth, that the end is not yet come: But afterwards he sayth thus; <hi>And
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118009:11"/> the Gospel of the kingdome of God shall be preached in all the world for a witnesse unto all Nations, and then shall the end come;</hi> Mark: 13. 10. This signe will be when that huge and terrible slaughter is passed, thereby it will be knowne; <hi>Zepha:</hi> 3. 8, 9. You may read the whole Prophet of <hi>Zephany,</hi> because he fully prophesieth of the last time: Now whether Christs prophesie will be accomplished will appeare, when first that great and bloody Battaile is passed, in which the Turke perisheth. The Reason of the Sermon on the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell of Gods kingdome, you must understand thus, (<hi>viz.</hi>) That all the kingdomes of this world shall be destroyed, and the kingdome of God of which wee shall speake more anon in its proper Chapter, and moreover you must understand, that, whereas Christ makes heavy complaint against false Christs, and false Prophets, that by them in these last Times if it were possible the very Elect might be seduced, <hi>Math:</hi> 24. 27. Namely, into Errours, and sayth expressely, <hi>Luke 18. 8. Thinkest thou that the Sonne of Man at his Comming will finde Faith on Earth?</hi> Which are very hard words, yet dares any man be so impudent as to give Christ the lye herein; Let men boast and be never so confident of their True Faith, yet here they must lay their hands on their Mouths, unlesse they will spet in Christs face for saying so.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Gospel of Gods kingdome shall be preached, and it shall be the signe of the End, it is to that purpose, that thereby appeareth the transcendent Love of God towards all men, <hi>Ezek. 18. 23. 32. Chap: 33. 11. 1 Tim:</hi> 2. 4, 5, 6. Now least he come and strike the Earth with Banishment; Therefore he hath promised that he will send unto us the Great Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> who shall convert the hearts of the Fathers to their Children, and the hearts of the Children to their Fathers, <hi>Mala:</hi> 4. Therefore when the Day of Perdition of the wicked is past, then the Sonne of Righteousnesse will arise in the eternall Gospel of the kingdome of Heaven, and then the great Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> shall be revealed in his Sermon, which will not be a Sermon sayd in such words as I have heard ere now, it will be sayd Love, wee must Love one another, whereby it will be knowne that wee are of God, and are his Children, 1 <hi>Joh: 4. 7. Chap: 5. Joh:</hi> 13. 34, 35. For Love is the Covenant of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Mala:</hi> 2. 10. And by this Sermon of Love, <hi>Elias</hi> will turne the hearts of the Fathers and of the Children one to another, and prepare the Way for the Lord, which commeth, for he is an Angel,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118009:11"/> and a Messenger of the Lord Zebaoth; <hi>Chap: 2. ver:</hi> 7. and <hi>Chap:</hi> 3. and the same Angel by whose Lusture the whole world shall be enlightned, <hi>Revel:</hi> 18. Thus will it be Light in the Time of the Evening, <hi>Zacha:</hi> 14. 7. Therefore the Gospel of his kingdome, will be begunne by his Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> who is yet in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; for it is the Evangelist of <hi>Sion</hi> which is promised to <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and the same Messenger, which brings to all <hi>Israel,</hi> both to the Jewes and Gentils a joyfull Message and eternall Gospel, for that Reason is he termed an Evangelist, <hi>Isaiah 40. 9. Chap:</hi> 41. 25, 27. In the Originall Tongue it does not signifie a Preacher, but so, I will give to <hi>Jerusalem</hi> an Evangelist, <hi>Chap: 52. 7 Nehemiah</hi> 1. 15. And this is properly the Angel with the eternall Gospel, <hi>Revel:</hi> 14. 6. Which foretold also hitherto the destruction of the Great Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which is the false Christendome, and the reestablishing of the kingdome of God, and of <hi>Israel.</hi> Thus you are exactly to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, and to be fully perswaded that at the preaching of <hi>Elias</hi> and of the Gospel of the kingdome in the whole world, that there will then be Revealed the onely true and saving Faith and Religion, and then there will be one Flocke, and one Pastor, <hi>John</hi> 10. 16. Which should move us to rejoyce heartily at it and be highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted thereby, because that at the last, this happy and joyfull Time will be at hand in which these things shall be accomplished, and then Men will not trouble their heads so much about Religion and Faith, whether they beleive rightly or no, but it will suffice that by this one word <hi>Love,</hi> the Right Religion and true Faith may be knowne, for <hi>Elias</hi> will put all the Prophets of <hi>Baal</hi> to the sword, and will destroy them by the sword of the Spirit wherewith he kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Antichrist, and makes an End of him, as the Type in the old Testament sheweth unto us, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. 21. even to the end; which false Prophets have told unto the People, and to Kings, not onely other Gods, but have also enticed them unto Warres, that they and the people might perish together as hitherto it fell out.</p>
               <p>Therefore Antichrist which is the Lying Spirit, must be destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not onely with the bodily but also with the spiritual sword, of which read the 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>
                  <hi>Thessal: 2. 8. Isaiah 11. 4. Zach:</hi> 4. 6. Which sword of the Spirit is the word of God, <hi>Ephes: 6. 17. Heb. 4. 12. Revel:</hi> 19. 13. 15. Therefore you must understand and judge of it aright (namely) that Antichrist which is the lying Spirit in the mouths of all false Prophets, is not killed and destroyed with the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118009:12"/> hand, but with the Mouth, that is, with the Spirit of the Mouth of Jesus Christ, as the Scripture plainly expresseth; 2 <hi>Thess: 2. 8. Isaiah</hi> 11. 4. Which wee put you in minde of, because you may the better conceive of the sence, and meaning of the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Now this Antichrist, and all false Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> and false Christs, and Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> are those who say, come let us wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship other Gods, <hi>Deut:</hi> 13. 13. the same will <hi>Elias</hi> reveale unto you at his Comming; it is not fit for me, neither doth it belong to my office, but his it is that hath the Spirit of whom it is foretold, 4 <hi>Esdras</hi> 11. 37. and 12. 31, 32, 33. who shall set them a life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgement of God, as <hi>Elias</hi> did with the others, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. and will openly rebuke, convince, and condemne them, and will teach againe the people the true Faith, Religion, and Worship of God, and will announce to the Remnant of the people Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and pleasant things, and an eternall Redemption, and refresh them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Lord commeth and the day of Judgement, the great and terrible day of the Lord, the like never was, nor will come hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 4 <hi>Esdras 12. 34. Isaiah</hi> 2. 11. and <hi>Joel 2. 2. 2 Thessal:</hi> 1. 8. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now the Spirit commeth in, and from the North, and from the Rising of the Sunne (namely) in the North, where they are all asleepe, <hi>Math:</hi> 25. and his Face is shining as the Sunne, and bath the gratious Token on his Head, (to wit) That God before the End of the World will Raise the Sonne of Righteousnesse by the preaching of the Gospel of the kingdome of God to all Nations, and Kindreds, Languages, and People, <hi>Revel:</hi> 14. 6. And that God will take pitty on his people <hi>Israel;</hi> His feete are like to two fiery Pillars, wherewith he stands on the Sea and Land; that is, the secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and spirituall Antichrist, with an exceeding great Zeale; and it is <hi>Elias</hi> which distributeth the little opened Booke, as you shall know afterwards, on which the Spirit of Zeale of the Lord Zebaoth resteth, <hi>Isai: 9. 2. 7. Chap:</hi> 11. And it is that Lyon, which roareth, and thundereth, making Heaven and Earth Tremble; of which read 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  <hi>Esdras 12. 31. Jeremy 25. 30. Joel 3 16. Amos</hi> the first; And he will speedily come forth out of his Denne and the Cloud wherewith he is encompassed shall be put away, <hi>Jeremy</hi> 25. 38. and because I see him already comming, and heare him Roaring, therefore would I make you acquainted with it, <hi>Amos</hi> 3 7, 8. So that when he commeth you may know him, and he will be as a Father to the House of <hi>Juda</hi> and to those at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> Isaiah 22.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118009:12"/> 21, 22. And as you were told already, will Reunite the hearts of the Fathers and Children one towards another; Of this Angel, and his Comming, none for ought I know, hath prophesied among the Astrologers, unlesse <hi>Paulus Nagel,</hi> and <hi>Jacob Bohmen,</hi> of blessed Memories, who have been the Glory in the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Comming of <hi>Elias</hi> is so plainly foretold in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that God will send him before the last Day, <hi>Mala:</hi> 4. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thought good to intimate him the more unto you, that you may know him when he commeth, and you may thinke then on me; and it is none else but that Angel which is described in <hi>Revel:</hi> 10. and which riseth with the Morning Starre at the apparition and Revelation of Jesus Christ on his Day, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 22. and the Dawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Day, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 8. 20. and the Light, <hi>Zachary</hi> 14. 7. and the Day of the Lord, in which wee rejoyce so much, <hi>Psal.</hi> 118. 24. and the Sonne of Righteousnesse, <hi>Mala:</hi> 4. and with him appeareth the Woman clad witht he Sunne, the Congregation of the Lord, <hi>Revel:</hi> 12. and the glorious Luster whereby the whole earth is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, <hi>Chap:</hi> 18. and the signe of the Sunne of Man in Heaven, and the Comming of the Lord, <hi>Math: 24. 30. 2 Thessal:</hi> 2. 8. He that hath Eyes let him see, and he that hath eares let him heare, and he that hath understanding let him Judge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The Third Chapter. Of the Nativity of the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> how it is undone, and of what is prognosticated of it.</head>
               <p>WEE have made a Promise unto you in the Preface, that wee will not hold forth unto you, our <hi>Prognostication</hi> without the Holy Scripture, least you should imagine wee preach Fables and Lyes unto you; Now whereas every one would willingly know what Issue &amp; Event in all these Warres &amp;c the <hi>Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> will winn or have; Wee will therefore tell you that also which wee have seene on the Watching Tower, which I shall endeavour so farre to satisfie you, that you may not contradict me or give me the lye.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118009:13"/>
               <p>Now Concerning the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> I hope you will grant without deniall that it is the fourth Beast and Kingdome on Earth, of whom the Angel hath foretold to the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> Chap: 7. especially because at the End of the same Kingdome, the comming of the Sonne of Man is described, and after it there ariseth another Kingdome, which is called <hi>the Holy One,</hi> of which hereafter; Now the Angel describeth this fourth Kingdome thus; The fourth Beast will be the Kingdome on Earth which will be greater than all Kingdomes, and will devoure the whole world, trample, and grinde them; and then ten Kings will arise in the same Empire, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after these will succeed, and be more potent then the former, who shall abase and humble three Kings, and he shall speake words against the Most High, and trample upon the Saints of the Highest, and will presume to Alter Time and Lawes, and they shall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into his hands for a Time, Times, and halfe a Time; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Judgement will be give, so that his Power shall be taken away, trod underfoote from the bottome, even to the End: Now here is the Nativity of the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> which in the fourth of <hi>Esdras,</hi> is called <hi>the Eagle,</hi> and in the <hi>Revelations</hi> it is called <hi>the Beast,</hi> what manner of <hi>Prognostication</hi> doe you thinke this is? Now which is that Horne, which warreth against the Saints, hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, trampled on them, and made an End of them; the same of which wee Read also in <hi>Revel:</hi> 13. 7. can yee guesse it? or hath it not already been made knowne to you in a Booke published by one, calling it <hi>The Looking-Glasse of Monarkes;</hi> therein is more at large described the Nativity of the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> and of the Blasphemous Horne.</p>
               <p>What happened at the <hi>Prauge</hi> in the yeare 1618, and 1621? pray looke into the 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg> and 12<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Chapters of the <hi>Revelations;</hi> Now what will befall this Horne, Beast, and House, the Great Tower in <hi>Spaine</hi> will come to Ruine, your eyes shall behold it, and the Beames of the great House will breake for all its Posts and Foundation, begin already to shake, of which you may Read <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saiah 2. 15. Chap: 30. 25. Habba:</hi> 2 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. The Day is come in which the Lord will visit the Leviathan, both at Sea and Land, with his strong and revenging sword, and will destroy the great Whale at Sea; <hi>Isaiah</hi> 27. Therefore doe not beleive the Peace, for the Lord Zebaoth hath bent his Bow, and layed deadly Arrowes on it; he hath prepared his Arrowes for Destruction;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118009:13"/> Therefore that Crosse also must be crucifyed which hath crossed so many Thousands of soules, as you well know, and hath Hanged them up here and there; Therefore the Spirit sayth thus; <hi>Woe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee thou Destroyer, when thou hast done destroying, thou thy selfe also shalt be destroyed,</hi> Isaiah 33. for as one hath wrought so shall he receive his Reward also, neither Counsell nor Deed will helpe.</p>
               <p>Now wee Read in the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> Chap: 7. 11. and 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Esdras</hi> 12. and <hi>Revel:</hi> 19. 20. with this unanimous witnesse that the Beast and Eagle shall be burnt with Fire, and shall be cast into the fiery Lake, which burneth with Fire and Brimstone; This is its Nativity and astrologicke propheticall <hi>Prognostication,</hi> which is made for the <hi>Romane Empire</hi> and Blasphemous Horne, for so many Yeares agoe; and that by Angells which are farre better Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of it, then our Almanack-makers and false Prophets, which love to flatter, and indulge themselves with the false Prophet, the Pope at <hi>Rome;</hi> and seduce the Beast to warre against the Saints, to perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, destroy, and roote them quite out; Therefore he shall receive alike reward with the Beast; Read <hi>Isaiah 44. 25, 26. Chap:</hi> 47. 12, 13, 14, 15. Why have you not made a Nativity for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Eagle?</hi> Nay you know not your owne Nativities, then how can you calculate them for others? doe but Read in the aforesaid quoted places of the Holy Scripture; Now wee let you know this that the Body of the Beast and Eagle is already kindled, and stands in a Glowing Heate, nay it flames out already, and no man can quench this Fire; But this is onely the beginning of it, and it will be more incensed by the foure Destroying Angells, so that the Blood shall reach even to the Horses Bridles by the space of 1600 Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, <hi>Revel:</hi> 14. 20. Therefore I can tell you no other, but that which I have observed already on my watching Tower; if it be not so, or will not come to passe in the like manner, then chide me, but if it so happen, then thinke not on me, but on him that hath revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it to me, who is the Spirit of the Prophets; Therefore, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is come upon the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> and it is the finall Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Three Times and a halfe are almost expired, and the sett Time 1650, the period of the Great House, is come to an end, then reckon backe of 350 yeares, then the Lyon out of the Forrest hath sett the Eagle already before Judgement; the execution will come as Lightning, unexpectedly, and the Earth shall Tremble at it, and be afraid; 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  <hi>Esdras</hi> 12. 3. Now Judgement is come not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118009:14"/> onely upon the Eagle and the Beast, but also upon all other Beasts, and upon all the Kings of the Earth; Read <hi>Zephany</hi> the 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> and the 8<seg rend="sup">th</seg>; <hi>Esay</hi> 2. 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. 22, 23, and 24 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <hi>Jeremy</hi> 25. For the wrath of God, and his heavy, and finall Judgement is come upon all the Heathens to destroy them, which have ruined, and destroyed the Earth, <hi>Revel:</hi> 11. 18. For the great Trumpet in Heaven in <hi>Anno</hi> 1618 hath sounded this Judgement, and indeed the Iron Rodd stands ready here, and is against Kings; <hi>Psal: 2. 9. Revel: 2. 27. Chap: 12. 5. Chap:</hi> 19. 15. Therefore this our Prognostication, (namely,) that all Kingdomes and Kings of this world will goe to wracke, and indeed, that in so few yeares, that hardly it will be beleived, though it should be told; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no prefixt Time concerning it, because it is already so nigh at hand; Therefore there will be wonderfull Alterations in Governments, many High Potentates, and all great things, and high Persons will suddenly come to an end; <hi>Isaiah</hi> 2. One House after another, will goe to Ruine and Decay, one mischance and misery will fall upon the other; <hi>Chap: 24. Jeremy</hi> 25. And Seaven Times seavenfold Plagues; such Calamities there will be, that the like hath never been seene on Earth, since Men were from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Creature, <hi>Daniel 12. Math: 24. 21. Luke</hi> 21. 26.</p>
               <p>Now when the Turke hath made that great slaughter, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe perish also, then indeed the Gospel of the Kingdome will be preached in all the world, but then the Devill also will send abroad his Prophets, Apostles, and Ministers, according to the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Viol, which will be the three unclean Spirits, as they are spoken of, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel:</hi> 16. 13, 14. They then will seduce and entice the Kings of the Earth, and Gog and Magog also, which is the great Duke in <hi>Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hoch,</hi> and <hi>Thubal,</hi> not the Turke, to goe to the Warres on that great Day of the Almighty, then all the Heathens the Kings of the Earth, the Beast, the last Romane Emperour, together with the false Prophet, the Pope at <hi>Rome,</hi> and Gog and Magog, with all his Hoast shall come to the Hills of <hi>Israel,</hi> and to the valley of <hi>Jehosa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> and there they shall be judged of God at the glorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Jesus Christ, and the Beast and the false Prophet are layd hold on, and shall be cast alive into the fiery Poole; of which read the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Ezdras 13. Isaiah 24. 21, 22. Ezek.</hi> 38, and 39. <hi>Joel 3. Zach:</hi> 14. 3. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This exceeding great warlike preparations and gatherings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118009:14"/> of the Heathen, shall be caused by the Returning of the Tenne Tribes of <hi>Israel,</hi> and the Returning of the <hi>Jewes</hi> to their Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Countrey, whom the Heathens intended to destroy, which the Lord judgeth; Now when you shall see and heare of this signe, that these preparations for Warres beginne to happen, then be assured most firmely, that the Comming of the Lord is at hand, which wee most faithfully doe intimate unto you for your direction.</p>
               <p>But now to tell you, who shall be the last Emperour, I have not seene, but I guesse, that the Lilly will put on the Crowne and Name of the last Beast will containe the Number 666. But I am not sure of it, for I am no Prophet, or Soothsayer, but am counted a lyar as all men are, Neverthelesse, the Time will speedily discover it, and it is difficult and dangerous to particularize and poynt at, therefore wee commit it to God and the Time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The Fourth Chapter. What manner of Empire will succeed, after the <hi>Romane Empire</hi> is ended, and who shall take possession of the Kingdome.</head>
               <p>THe Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> answers plainly in expresse words, <hi>Chap:</hi> 2. and 7. saying, <hi>But the Kingdome, and the Power and Glory of the Kingdome, under the whole Heaven, or under all Heavens, shall be given to the People of the Saints of the most High, whose kingdome is an everlasting kingdome, and all Kings shall serve and obey him;</hi> also <hi>ver: 14. And the Antient gave to the Sonne of Man, Power, Glory, and Dominion, all People, Nations, and Languages, shall serve him; his Power is everlasting, which shall not be taken away, and his Dominion shall not be destroyed:</hi> Here is a <hi>Quaere</hi> whether this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be of this World, for the kingdome of Christ is not of this world, <hi>John</hi> 18. 36. To which <hi>Daniel</hi> answers, saying, <hi>Chap: 2. 44. In the Times of these kingdomes the God of Heaven will Raise a kingdome which shall never be destroyed, and that kingdome shall not be left to a strange People, it will Destroy and Grinde all these kingdomes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118009:15"/> its selfe will endure for ever; As you have seene a Stone cut off from a Mountaine, without Hands, and that it brake in Peices, the Iron, the Brasse, the Clay, the Silver, and the Gold:</hi> Now seeing the God of Heaven will establish this kingdome, therefore it is not of this world, but necessarily it is from Heaven, and though it is and shall be under Heaven and on Earth, and that the Saints of God after the order of <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> shall be Kings, and Priests on Earth; Therefore it is a Holy kingdome, because meerly Righteous, and no sinners shall be therein, for the Devill is cast into the Abysse, that he shall seduce no more; of which Read, <hi>Psal:</hi> 45. 47. 93. 97. 99. 110. and many other Psalmes, also the 72 &amp;c. <hi>Isaiah 60. 21, 22. Revel: 5. 10. Chap: 20. 3, 4, 5. Isaiah 2. Mich: 4. Obediah ver. 21. Zach:</hi> 14. 9. Then shall be accomplished the Eight Psalme, and whatever is prophesied in the Psalmes; and Prophets of Christs kingdome.</p>
               <p>Now if any should chance to deride, mocke, and calumniate, and brand it with the word <hi>Millenaryes;</hi> let him reade his owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Revel: 22. 19. Mala:</hi> 4. He that denies the kingdome of God shall perish with the kingdome of the Devill, if he repents not, and beleiveth not the Gospel of the kingdome which Christ causeth to be published, <hi>Math:</hi> 24. 14. therefore let every one stand to his hazard, 2 <hi>Thes:</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. If it be asked what kinde of Stone was it which was pulled without hands from the Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> which striketh at the Feet of the great Image of the foure Kingdomes of the Earth making it fall, and commeth to an end? Answer; It is that Stone which lyeth before the High Priest <hi>Joshua,</hi> Zach: 3. 9. Which is called <hi>Zema, Oriens,</hi> and in the 8 verse, and <hi>Chap:</hi> 6. 12, 13. The same Stone which now shall be layd for the Foundation of him that buildeth the Temple of the Lord, and the Citie <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> which Stone the Babylonian builders have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto rejected, as it is written, <hi>Isaiah 28. 16. Psal:</hi> 118. 22. Which is the spirituall Rocke, 1 <hi>Corinth:</hi> 10. and indeed is nothing else but the glorious Epiphany of Jesus Christ at his Comming, and the Revelation of the Sonne of Man at his Day, 2 <hi>Thessal: 2. 8. Luke</hi> 17. 24. &amp;c. It is the Child which shall feed all Nations with an Iron Rod, <hi>Revel:</hi> 12. 5. Therefore take notice of the second Psalme; for now is the Time of it.</p>
               <p>It is written in the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> that the Stone comes off from Mount <hi>Sion</hi> without mans hands; what is meant thereby? Answer
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118009:15"/> The Prophet <hi>Zacha:</hi> 4. 6, 7. Because it is a spirituall Stone, and is the Spirit of Christ, the Spirit of Judgement, as wee have shewed unto you, 4 <hi>Esdras 2. 31, 32. Isaiah 11. 4. 2 Thessal:</hi> 2. 8.</p>
               <p>Therefore wee are not told of a worldly kingdome in the Gospel of that kingdome, but of a spirituall kingdome which God esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blisheth without Hands and power of Men; Therefore it will abide for ever; now this kingdome is and will be the kingdome of <hi>Israel,</hi> which the Lord Zebaoth will establish againe through the true king <hi>David</hi> Jesus Christ, who is the most holy, who shall, and is anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be king for ever over the house of <hi>David,</hi> for he will be also Pastor, King, and Priest after the order of <hi>Melchisedech, Psal: 110. Ezek: 37. 16. 24. Zacha: 6. 13. Daniel 9. 24. Ezek: 34. 23. Jeremy</hi> 23. 5, 6. Thus <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Juda</hi> shall be helped, as God hath promised, <hi>Chap:</hi> 33. 16. They will no more have two, but one Head, their true and loving <hi>David,</hi> and Messias, whom indeed hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto they have not Received, but now they will seeke after him, <hi>Hosea 1. 11. Chap: 3. 4. 5. 2 Chron:</hi> 15. 3. whom the others have crucified, these now will bewayle him heartily in true sorrow and Repentance, <hi>Zacha:</hi> 12. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. And all the kindred of the Earth will howle and weepe with them when they shall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Comming, <hi>Math: 24. 30. Revel:</hi> 1. 7. Then shall be accomplished the words of Christ, <hi>Math:</hi> 23. 29 Saying, <hi>You shall not see me untill you say, Blessed is he that commeth in the Name of the Lord,</hi> then they shall know him when they exalt him, <hi>Joh:</hi> 8, 28. Hitherto the Gospel could prevaile nothing in the Cities of <hi>Israel,</hi> and is accomplished what Christ sayd, <hi>Math:</hi> 10. 23. But now the Gospel of the kingdome shall be preached unto them also, and they will Receive it of the Evangelist who is promised to <hi>Jerusalem; Isaiah 40. 9. Chap:</hi> 41. 26. Which is none else but <hi>Eliakim,</hi> or <hi>Elias, Chap: 22. 21. Mala:</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>What shall wee now prognosticate here in this our new <hi>Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacke;</hi> such Newes which never was knowne before? It is this; That the Lord will Reestablish the kingdome of <hi>Israel;</hi> and free the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and gather together the scattered <hi>Israel,</hi> and turne away their Captivity, and though they be thrust out even to the end of heaven, yet will the Lord fetch them from thence againe, and be mindfull of his Covenant, which he hath sworne to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his seede for ever; of which you may read; <hi>Deut: 4. 30, 31. Chap: 30. Isaiah.</hi> 11. 11. and <hi>Chap: 27. 12, 13. Chap:</hi> 51. 10, 11.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118009:16"/>
                  <hi>Jere: 31. Ezek:</hi> 34, 35, 36, 37 Chapters: <hi>Chap: 29. 25, 26, 27, 28, 29. Daniel 9. 24. Hosea 1, 2, 3. Joel 3. Amos</hi> 9. 11. and <hi>Mica: 2. 12, 13. Chap: 4. Chap:</hi> 5. 7. and <hi>Chap: 7. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. Haba: 3. 9. Zepha: 3. 10. Hagg: 2. 22. Zacha:</hi> 9. 13. &amp;c. <hi>Chap: 10. Chap: 12. 13, 14. Mala:</hi> 3. 6. &amp;c. Briefly, it is so plainly prophesied in the Psalmes and Prophets, that <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Juda</hi> shall have deliverance, and Returne againe to <hi>Sion,</hi> that it cannot be exprest more plainely; The Apostle calls it a Mystery, <hi>Rom:</hi> 11. 25. giveth a warning to the Gentils to take heed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lofty and high minded, because Blindnesse happened to <hi>Israel;</hi> Therefore when the fullnesse of the Gentils is come in, then salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion happeneth to all <hi>Israel;</hi> because from <hi>Sion</hi> shall come their Deliverer to take away their Iniquity, and deliver them from all their sinnes; <hi>Rom. 11. 25, 26, 27. Psal: 130. 8. Psal:</hi> 22. 28, 29. and so Christ himselfe sayth, <hi>Luk:</hi> 21. 24. They shall fall by the sword and be carryed Captive among all the Heathens, and <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> shall be sacked by the Heathens, till the Times of the Heathens are accomplished; But now whether the Time of the Heathens be expired, and the kingdomes of the World fall home to the Lord and his Anoynted; You may enquire of the Angel who hath soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the seventh Trumpet, and of the Blazing Starre, <hi>Anno</hi> 1618; and perhaps other Messengers from Heaven will come and tell of it; Therefore for my part I can discover nothing more from my Tower and Guard; But what I heard of the Lyon; <hi>Isaiah 21. 8. 4 Esdras 11. 37, 38. Jeremy 25. 30 Joel</hi> 3. 16.</p>
               <p>Now in case any one should except against, he excepts not against me, but against him who hath placed and sett me on the Tower for a Watchman to tell you of it, and it is effected to that end, that you with all the Saints should Rejoyce for and in this kingdome of God, but the kingdome of God and <hi>Israel,</hi> shall not be established by the Hands of Men, and not by humane might, sword, and Power, but in the Spirit, and through the Spirit, and no otherwise; and to this, none will lift up so much as a sticke, much lesse a sword or speare; for it will not be any worldly kingdome, but the Scepter of the Mouth of him that commeth will slay them all.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Stone is come downe from the Mount <hi>Sion</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Hands of Men, because this will be done, not by a Warlike Power, but through his Spirit; <hi>Zach:</hi> 4. 6 Therefore he that shall, or will be a partaker of this kingdome, let him become a Jew,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118009:16"/> and Confessor of Jesus Christ the Sonne of God, what manner of confession this is, <hi>Elias</hi> will tell it at his Comming.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The Fifth Chapter. What manner of Nativity is set for the Dragon, and the Devill, who is God and Prince of this world, as also for his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel and Servants.</head>
               <p>TO this Answers the Prophet, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 24. 21. Namely, That the Prince on high with his Hoast shall be visited, gathered, cast into Prison, and lockt up: The same we read also <hi>Revel:</hi> 20. Now the Dragon is a God, and Prince of this World, 2 <hi>Corinth: 4. 4. Joh: 14. 30. Chap:</hi> 12. 31. dwelleth and ruleth on high in the Ayre under Heaven, and carries on his affaires among the Children of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, (or infidelity) <hi>Ephes: 2. Chap:</hi> 6. 12. Thus the Devill hath in the world his kingdome in the Ayre; where his Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Powers and Angels dwell (Namely) unto the Globe and Spheare of <hi>Luna;</hi> as farre as the Darknesse reacheth, which wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not see; because our Eyes are not opened, and the Devills king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome on high is spirituall; But the Dragon is become so high by Reason of Mans fall, for his sinne from the beginning of the world, and because he hath caused Man to fall, therefore he must also fall, as he is fallen also already; And I have seene him lying on the Ground bruised and crushed in his Backe, Head, Hands, and Feete, and in his Wings also, lying Dead, and these words lay written by it; <hi>Violenta violenta, Flagitiosa, scilicet Mors:</hi> That which I have seene also that he was thrust out; <hi>viz.</hi> I saw a House which was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, from, or above the Earth, there was a Great Gate towards the North, which was opened, there came one to stand in the middest of the Gate as I conceived it was the Angel of the sixth Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, he spyed Sathan walking to and fro under the formes in the same Roome, in the shape of a Red Dogg, he was very loath to get out of that Roome in which he abode so long, but he must come out, he came forth by the Right Foote of the Angel that stood in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118009:17"/> the middest of the Gate, I thought to my selfe he might bite him in the heele, and my eye was fixed on it, but he durst not meddle with him as I perceived, neither did he; Now when Satan was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out, then the Angel lifted up his face to God with hearty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward sighing, saying, Ah now let the Lord say Amen, seven times, I constered it thus; that Satan should never come againe into the Roome; Thus the Gate is opened to the Angel which no man can shutt; But what one he is <hi>Elias</hi> the Prophet at his comming will tell it; This vision I have seene in a Citty which beareth the key, namely, a Lyon with the key; In which Citie I have seene many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things besides: As how the Temple also was opened, and I have seene also the Lord Rising from the Dead.</p>
               <p>The vision of the open Gate I have seene <hi>Anno</hi> 1625. the first of <hi>January</hi> in the Morning betwixt six and seaven on New yeares Day; Now when Christ commeth then will you see this vision, and you will behold it with your bodily eyes, and rejoyce with me heartily, and be thankfull unto the Lord for it. And least you should thinke I hold forth unto you Visions and Fables, therefore you may read the Truth your selves, namely, that Satan the great Dragon was turned out and cast forth out of Heaven upon the Earth, <hi>Isaiah, Chap: 14. v:</hi> 12. &amp;c. <hi>Revelt. 12. v:</hi> 9. &amp;c. and seeing he was cast forth made him so fierce and wrathfull, for he knoweth that his time is but short, therefore was he so enraged from the yeare 1618. when his being cast out was plainely intimated and demonstrated to the world in the Head Citie of the Lyon, even till now both at Sea and Land, and his Rageing will begin afresh, though the people talke of peace, yet perdition will fall on them suddenly as travaile upon a woman with Child, and they shall not be able to escape, and now more violently then was done hitherto, experience will testifie of it fully, both by Sea and Land, and you shall not need to contradict me.</p>
               <p>Now is the Time come of the great Warres and battailes, the like was not since the world was, nor shall be, namely, betwixt the two potent Princes, between the great Prince and Archangell <hi>Michael,</hi> and betwixt the Prince of this world the Dragon, the old Serpent the Devill; For the great Prince <hi>Michael</hi> who stirred now to guide his people <hi>Israel,</hi> as it is prophesied in <hi>Daniel</hi> 12. hath fought with the Dragon and conquered him, and thrust him out by the blood of the Lambe, and through the word of their Testimony, and through
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118009:17"/> their fidelity unto death; so that he can no more accuse the servants of God day night before God, and there is no place to be found for him in Heaven, therefore is now the joyfull time once come that the people of <hi>Israel</hi> shall be delivered, because the 70 weekes and the 1335 dayes are expired, where the iniquity will be forgiven, and wickednesse will be at an end, the sinne blotted out, and the eternall Righteousnesse is brought againe which hitherto was lost through <hi>Adam,</hi> therefore every vision and prophesie shall be fullfilled, and the most holy to be anoynted a King for his kingdome, <hi>Dan: 9. 24. Acts</hi> 3. 19, 20, 21. The abomination of desolation shall be aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and the Sanctuary shall be cleansed againe, for the 2300 dayes come to an end, <hi>Dan:</hi> 8. 14. Therefore as in former times the Law and the Prophets have prophesied to <hi>John the Baptist,</hi> even so it is now also, all prophesies goe till <hi>Elias</hi> who is the last Prophet who is promised in its time to us before the comming of the Lord, with him they cease, and every prophesie is accomplished, &amp; from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth no Prophet or prophesie will be, and through him also the impure Spirit will be rooted out from the Earth, of which you may Read <hi>Zachary</hi> 13. And every one shall have for himselfe a new Baptisme for his sinne and uncleannesse, like an open fountaine, like as <hi>Jordan</hi> was to <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> 2 Kings 5 Now as <hi>John</hi> of old baptized with water unto Repentance, so <hi>Elias</hi> is to baptize us with the holy Ghost not long after these dayes, which is God the Lord of this baptisme and of these wholesome fountaines is prophesied, <hi>Isaiah 12. 3. Chap: 44. 3. Zacha: 12. 10. Chap: 13. Jere: 31. 33. Ezek: 11. 19, 20. Chap: 36. 25, 26, 27. Joel</hi> 2. 28. But he will baptize the wicked with fire and sword, as he did in times of old, therefore I can give you no other signe whereby you might observe all this then the signe of the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> who ascended to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in a fiery Chariot, and returneth also in the name of the Lord on a fiery Chariot, but who can brooke with the day of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, because it will be as fire, <hi>Mal:</hi> 3. and you shall heare and know it, if you have not already heard it, that never any man on the earth hath ever spoken so sharply, the Reason is because his Tongue is like a devouring fire, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 30. 27, 28, 30. &amp;c. which cansumeth and swalloweth up all, <hi>Chap:</hi> 42. 13, 14. and the Spirit of both witnesses of the old and New Testament resteth on him; he hath power to shutt and open heaven, to transmute water into Blood, and to strike the earth with all monner of plagues as often
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118009:18"/> as he pleases, <hi>Revel:</hi> 11. Whereas a Nativity is sett for the Devill and the Dragon, and he must come downe into the goale &amp; abysse, then with him downe must come all the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 24. 21. and the Beast, <hi>Revel:</hi> 19, 20, 21. and the Dragon in the Sea, <hi>Psal: 64. 12, 13, 14, 15. Isa:</hi> 27. And wee will tell you, what wee have seene in the vision of our Ward, namely, a number of Oxen and fatted Beasts driven together, because the King which prepareth for the nuptials of his Sonne will slay and kill these Oxen and fatted Beasts, <hi>Math: 22. 4. Psal:</hi> 68. 31. Therefore come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yee Gentils and hearken, and yee Nations take notice of it, read it your selves, <hi>Isa:</hi> 33. and observe the whole Chapter very well for all the hoast of heaven, <hi>Ephes: 2. 2. Chap:</hi> 6. 12. must downe and fall off as a leafe which is withered, therefore I have seene that all high lookes must come downe, and all those that strive for high things, and to be somewhat looked upon amongst men; but the Lord alone will be so high and exalted on that day, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 2. 11. It is a very hard word, <hi>Revel:</hi> 13. that the Dragon hath given his power, his stoole, his great power to the Beast, whereby it hath supprest and persecuted the Saints, and that those which dwell on the earth, and are earthly minded doe worship both the Beast and Dragon also, therefore the Beast together with the Dragon must into the poole which burneth for ever, <hi>Revel: 19 20. Chap:</hi> 20. 10. Seeing the Dragon is cast and throwne out of heaven, and must be flung into the Abysse and a seale putt upon him, so that he shall seduce no more, then there will be no more sinne and no more Death, but a fullnesse of joy and a pleasant being eternally, and wee have cause heartily to rejoyce, meditate of it, and comfort our selves therewith about it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The Sixth Chapter. What Astrologicall Prognostication is set for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, Sunne and Moone, the whole world, and all the creatures therein.</head>
               <p>SEing there is an usual discourse of Nativities among Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, therefore wee also will sett a Nativity for Heaven and the Astralls thereof, which shall be nothing else but a new birth, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118009:18"/> and transmutation, namely, that Heaven and Earth shall be renewed, Sunne Moone and Starres and all other creatures none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, you Mathematicians, Astronomers and Astrologers, have you never seene nor read it in the booke of Heaven, then make use of Spectacles, perhaps you may spy it yet, or can you not discover with the Astralobes, and observe what they say; for the whole Creature in Heaven and in Earth speake with one mouth of renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things, for the Creature also shall be delivered from the bondage of vanity and corruptiblenesse to a freedome of the glory of Gods Children, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 12. What doe you thinke of this say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? The Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> answers plainly to this Quaere. 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 13. Wee waite for a new heaven and a new earth, according to his promise in which dwelleth Righteousnesse;</hi> and so sayth the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> also <hi>Chap: 65. 17. Chap:</hi> 66. 22. This renewing will be done through a great motion, and transmutation, <hi>Haggai 2. 7. Heb:</hi> 12. 17. The Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> sayth, 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 3. 10. 12. That the Heaven will be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved with Cracking, that is, with a moving of their powers, as Christ sayes, <hi>Math:</hi> 24. 29. (as it were delivered from the bonds of their impurity wherewith they are hitherto bound, and defiled with sinne) <hi>Job</hi> 15. 15. and are fiery, that is, goe through the fire as gold and silver is cleansed and purified in the fire throughly, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 33. namely, which takes away all impurity and keepeth or preserveth the purer part; the concordance in the Psalme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it more plainely and calls it a transmutation, <hi>Psal:</hi> 102. 27. So that the substance and being remaineth, but the qualities which appertaine not to the purity, are taken away, then the heavens will praise the judgement of God when their iniquity is taken away, <hi>Psal. 50. 6. Psal.</hi> 8. 4. and declare his righteousnesse, <hi>Psal. 97. 6. Thou wilt change them as a garment, and they shall be transmuted, Psal:</hi> 102. 27. You may conceive of it thus, as a pure incombasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Linnen is cleansed from its impurity through fire, that it be very white new and pure; even so the heavens also shall be purified, and the earth also shall goe through the fire and be purged from the Curse and sinne, and the workes which are therein shall burne away, and this will be done not onely to heaven and earth, but also to all men, as the Apostle plainely saith, 1 <hi>Corinth:</hi> 3. 13, 14, 15. And Christ tells us, <hi>Mark: 9. 49. That every man shall be seasoned with fire;</hi> all this you shall be better informed of by him which commeth after me, <hi>viz. Elias.</hi> Seeing there will be such a sharpe processe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118009:19"/> as Christ and his two chiefest Apostles attest namely, that all must goe through the fire, even all men and all their workes, therefore I know no better advice to hold out in this sharpe and fiery Trial, but that we fit and prepare our selves for the comming of the Lord, in which time all this shall come to passe by a holy conversation, as St <hi>Peter</hi> doth exhort us unto and that wee suffer our selves to be baptized of <hi>Elias</hi> with fire and the holy Ghost, and with the salt of Wisdome be seasoned, then wee may hold out in the fire for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing indures in the fire but salt, of which <hi>Elias</hi> will tell you more, and be not refractory against him when he commeth to you with the fire of Judgement, and with a mighty sharpe punishment; but if yee be refractory, then the sword will destroy you, and the fire will consume you; Behold, I have told you of it aforehand fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned, fore-armed, <hi>Isa. 1. 20 Chap:</hi> 66. 16.</p>
               <p>If it be asked what manner of fire it will be, by and through it heaven and earth Sunne and Moone, and all the Starres shall be purged; from whence doth it come, and whither doth it returre? I have seene none else but the fiery Cherub which lyeth still before the gate of Paradice which must remove from thence at the Lords comming, and must give a free passage to the Tree of Life; This fire is the power of the opposite Element, and the last wrath, in which fire, Heaven, Earth, and all what therein is shall stand, and this shall be that fire also which is to fall upon God and Magog and on the great Multitude of those which intend to fight against him which is to come, <hi>Ezek: 38. 22. Chap: 39. 6. 4 Esdras</hi> 13. 10, 11. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this fire shall be cast also alive the Beast and the false Prophet, and have a fiery poole for their dwelling, and goe downe to the Abysse downe to the pit which is already prepared, since yesterday, and is wide and broad enough for the King, <hi>Isaiah 30. 33. Revel:</hi> 20. 20. Into which at the last shall be cast also Hell, Death, and the Devill, <hi>Chap:</hi> 21. 10 14 Seing the heavens shall be renewed, then the hoast of heaven, Sunne, Moone and Starres shall be renewed in this manner, that the luster of the Sunne shall be greater seaven times then it is now, and the luster of the Moone shall be such as the Sunne now hath, namely at that time when the Lord will dresse the wounds of his people, and heale their plagues, as it is plainely prophesied, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 30. 26. But before that time Sunne and Moone shall be darke and blacke, and the Starres fall downe from Heaven, alitle before Christs comming and will be ashamed before the Lord
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118009:19"/> that commeth, and before his terrible wrath at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Isa: 24. 23. Luke 21. 25. Revel:</hi> 6. 12, 13, 14. Therefore the Eclipses of the Sunne and Moone which we behold are a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of these great Eclipses which are to come; and Astrologers ought to consider the true cause of the Eclipses of the Sunne and Moone Naturally, that it is from sinne through which the heavens also were defiled and could not keep pure, <hi>Job</hi> 15. 15. When <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> transgressed and fell, and at the renovation they shall be pure agen: Moreover the Sunne and Moone receive their Eclipses by the sleering and envious looking or beholking the Darknesse, and of the Devill the Prince of Eclipses in the Ayre, who with his poysonous sleering and envious Eyes defyleth Sunne and Moone and Starres, no otherwise then as when a menstruous Woman de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth a pure glasse by looking in it, for the impurity of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man proceeds and hath its cause from sinne, and all wee are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and borne in such an impurity; Neither is the Gall in man a member created of God in man at the beginning, but is growne by and of eating the forbidden fruit and is a meere poyson which shall be taken away agen at the renovation of man, and of all things in the world (and by reason of sinne Christ must drinke Vineger mixt with Gall, <hi>Math: 27. 34. John</hi> 19. 29.) Then surely no more of any Eclipses will befall the Sunne and Moone, neither will the Moone be in an increase or decrease nor the night be so darke as it is now, neither will there be any such frosty Winters nor cold nor frost; because all opposite and contrary things will be taken away and cease; and as there was no enmity at all at the beginning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Woman and the Serpent, betwixt the Wolfe and the Lamb, then there will be not any strife or enmity neither at that time, then will the Lord make a Covenant with the beasts of the field with the birds of the Ayre, and the Wormes on the earth, <hi>Hosea 2. 18. Isaiah 11, 6, 7, 8, 9. Chap: 43. 19, 20. Chap:</hi> 65. 25. And this is it, which the Apostle speakes of, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8. 21. that the creature shall be freed from the bondage of vanity, therefore the eternall Gospel of the kingdome of God and of the glorious and joyfull Redemption is annuntiated, not onely to man, but also to heaven and earth, Sunne Moone and Staares, and to all other Creatures under the whole heaven and on earth in an eternall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from all Evill, and from sinne the Devill and Death, at which Redemption the Glory of the Children of God will be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118009:20"/> but then revealed, for the which all the Creatures together with us have waited anctiously and sighingly, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8. 19 22. Hee that hath eares let him heare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The Seaventh Chapter. What Prognostication is set for Generalls, Officers and Souldiers, and other Commissaryes and Collectors of Contributions.</head>
               <p>WHereas this Generation delights in Warre happily I may doe them service, because I must Prognosticate for them also, as they might be pleased with it; therefore I can say nothing else, then that which I have seene on the Guard, namely, Warre and the sword, and indeed more terrible then ever it was, therefore whereas they dreame now of a peace, then the warres will more fiercely come on, therefore let them not be sad and melancholy if they are disbanded for a little season, for I see the sword comming over all the Inhabitants of the earth, <hi>Jere:</hi> 25. 29. If it commeth upon all, surely at the last it will come upon you also: Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe hath made a Prognostication for your Nativity, viz: <hi>Math: 26. 52. Those that take the sword shall perish by the sword,</hi> unlesse such men did turne betimes and seriously repent, and confessed their murtherous deeds and heavy sinnes at the Crosse with that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, happily they might finde pardon and Remission, otherwise the place where they must goe is called <hi>Armageddon,</hi> that is, damned Warriors, <hi>Revel:</hi> 16. 16. But that none may come to that torment I will impart unto you a good advice from the Mouth of him who hath before set the Prognostication to your Nativity, which is this, viz: <hi>Whatsoever you would have men to doe or not to doe to you, so you must doe or not doe to them,</hi> Math: 7. 12 <hi>John the Baptist</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it thus, being asked of Souldiers what are wee to doe? hee told them, <hi>Doe violence to no man, neither accuse any falsely, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with your wages,</hi> Luke 3. 14. Whither <hi>John</hi> by this answer held warring lawfull or allowed of, as most men pretend he did, I will not dispute it, neither does it belong to me in my place; <hi>Elias</hi> will
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118009:20"/> tell it you when he comes, him you may aske; But this good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell and doctrine of St <hi>John,</hi> is no where better observed and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then among the Souldiers under the Lyon which carryeth the Sword and Arrowes, therefore is he the more blessed and will finde the first mercy among or before all others for to enter into Gods kingdome; for as wee deale with others, so wee shall be dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and wherewith one sinneth, therewith shall he be punished, <hi>Wisdome 11. 17. Isaiah</hi> 33. How can any man justifie that which his owne Conscience condemneth him for, unlesse that a man would willfully bring a judgement upon his owne head, <hi>Isa: 6. 20. Rom:</hi> 2. therefore doe not erre; God will not be mocked, <hi>Gal:</hi> 6. 7. But if the Lyon with the sword and arrowes should feele the Collicke in his Body, he will hardly finde a Physition to Cure him, neither would Purge or Clyster helpe, which I am much afraid of, for when the arrowes are, then the sword will sinke also: Though men la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour very much to Justifie Warre, however it seemes they will be sensible that the Warre produceth no good, and begin to cry, <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la salus Bello, Pacem te possimus omnes;</hi> But it is too late, they should have sung this song sooner, for peace is taken away from the earth, they must destroy one another, <hi>Revel:</hi> 6. 4. and the sentence holds which stands in <hi>Genesis 9. 6. Hee that sheds mans blood, his blood shall be shed againe through man;</hi> the Reason is, because man is Created after Gods Image; Therefore he that disfigureth his Image, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figureth Gods Image, his owne, and such a one sinneth in a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold manner, and will hardly be excused; what a heavy sinne is it to shed mans blood, none knowes it but he alone which considereth that wee are dearly bought and redeemed through the blood of the Sonne of God, and this is the Reason why the eating of blood is forbidden as well in the New as in the old Testament, <hi>Act. 15. 29. Chap: 21. 25. Gen: 9. 4. Levit:</hi> 7. 26, 27. because wee are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and bought by blood, wherefore it should be holy unto us in remembrance of our Redemption, <hi>Levit:</hi> 17. 14. for life is in the Blood, now what God hath sanctifyed no man ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, <hi>Act:</hi> 10. 15. He that knows it better let him, but hee must answer it to the holy Ghost who hath commanded it so, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 29. But because Souldiers say, when wee cannot get our pay, wee are then forced to plunder? Answer, <hi>John the Baptist</hi> had nothing to doe with such Souldiers, neither can he impart any Councell to them, therefore they must goe some where else, namely, to the false
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118009:21"/> Prophets which seduceth the beast, and to his Consorts, to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther false Prophets which entice the Kings of the earth to fight, they may read their Nativity, <hi>Revel:</hi> 16. 13, 14: It is horrible to heare such false Prophets Pray to God, namely, to their God whom they serve as their Father, <hi>John</hi> 8 44. to grant his blessing that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands may be slaine, when it is done then goe to the Temple and sing to their God a <hi>Te Deum Laudamus,</hi> and intreat him to continue such blessings; The adverse party doe the like, which of them be the best, judge yee? However that they may have a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, there is another <hi>John</hi> who sayth in his first Epistle <hi>Chap: 3. 15. Whosoever hateth his brother is a murtherer, and from the evill one,</hi> and moreover he sayes, <hi>Who is a murtherer of men, and yee know that no murtherer hath eternall life abiding in him;</hi> now if he be a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer that hateth his brother, much more if he be such a one that killeth his Neighbour with his hand; Let every one judge as he pleaseth, I am not a Judge though I announce Judgement, but I am onely a Watchman that performeth his Masters will. But I cannot set any other Prognostication for Souldiers then I have seene and knowne it in the Propheticall Astrology, namely, that all Warres with their furious and bloody accoutrements shall be burnt and consumed with fire. <hi>Isa: 9. 5. Psal:</hi> 46. 10. therefore the time will come very shortly in which the swords shall be turned into plough-shares, and their speares into pruning hookes, <hi>Isa: 2 Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> 4. but it must be first the contrary, plough-shares must be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into swords, and pruining hookes must be turned into speares, it is practised now, they take them away from the ploughs, for the weeds must be gathered as it is written, <hi>Math:</hi> 13. 40, 41, 42. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Harvest commeth, the great Corne-harvest and vintage, <hi>Revel: 14. Joel</hi> 3. 13, 14. and the heavy day of the Lord, of which Read <hi>Isaiah 13. Joel</hi> 2. and here and there in the Prophets; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the joyfull comming of the Lord shall be, then wee shall have a true and firme peace, and not before that time, let every man make his account accordingly. The greatest Calamities, Warres, and shedding of blood, all is to come yet, and neere at hand, many unheard of strange and severall plagues and miseries are comming, great famines, pestilence and dearth, and yet will soone passe over, and in such heavy calamities God will provide for his owne that feare him and call upon his Name, these shall be delivered, as it is promised, <hi>Mal: 3. 16, 17, 18. Chap:</hi> 4. And as wee have made
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118009:21"/> mention above in the Preface of those that have the Seale of God in their forehead, <hi>Revel:</hi> 7. 3. Now all those which are concerned herein in the abomination of desolation, which vexe, torment, and plague poore people with contribution and strayning, and such like wayes, especially if they seeke their owne profit, thereby they not onely onerate themselves with great sinnes by their Tyranny, but they participate also of other mens sinnes, and bring on their owne heads a double judgement and heavy damnation, because by their sucking extortion they eate up and devoure the poore people, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah 3. Hab: 2. 6. Amos</hi> 5. 11, 12. They have away their Reward, and must expect Judgement without mercy; but he that sheweth mercy to his neighbour shall obtaine mercy againe, and he that is peaceable shall possesse the kingdome of God, and be called the childe of God, <hi>Math: 5. 7, 8. Luke</hi> 6. 36. Therefore though one have an ill ascendent and a bad Nativity, yet he may put away this evill ascendent, and give way for another ascendent, otherwise what should the Scripture avayle us, if wee should subdue an Ill Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, which ascendents the Evill Spirit in man worketh, and not the naturall Astralls above in the Firmament, which onely shew what Ascendent there is in us, of which yee Astrologers nere take notice; What manner of nativity would you have sett for the Theife on the Crosse? Thus a man that stands in the new Birth and walketh with God, and God in him, needs not be affrayd at all of the signes in heaven, <hi>Jere:</hi> 10. 2. For he hath another ascendent in him which is the Spirit of Christ, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8. Therefore the true Astrology con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in the consideration of the Astralls and of the Spirit which man inwardly hath in himselfe, and by no meanes in the visible A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stralls and heaven, and you are farre wide from knowing the true Astrology, neither the visible or invisible else you would make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prognostications, however Judgement doth not belong to mee but to the Spirit of Judgement, and hee that hath that Spirit name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of <hi>Elias,</hi> that is of the Lords.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118009:22"/>
               <head>The Eighth Chapter. What manner of Nativity and Prognostication is sett for the great whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and her Merchants, and those that went awhoring with her?</head>
               <p>TO this answers the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> Chap: 13. namely, <hi>Come downe to the dust thou Virgin Daughter Babylon,</hi> Chap: 47. her Prognostication is read also in <hi>Jeremy 51. And that a people will come from the North and shall make her Land desolate;</hi> whether it be done yet? Therefore when <hi>Babylon</hi> shall fall and falleth, then the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> and the Children of <hi>Juda</hi> will come together weeping, they will make hast, and to seeke the Lord their God they will enquire after the way to <hi>Sion,</hi> and set their faces that way, and will be joyned with the Lord in an eternall Covenant which shall never be broken. What manner a one is that <hi>Babylon,</hi> who can tell it us which is alwayes so much threatned, <hi>Jere:</hi> 51. The Spirit of prophesie describeth her, <hi>Revel:</hi> 17. she sits on many waters, and that the Kings of the Earth have committed fornication with her, and are made drunke with the wine of her whoredome: the Spirit sayth further, shee sitteth on a scarlet Red Beast, full of blasphemies, having seaven heads and ten hornes, and truely this woman is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently set forth but because it is added that it is a mystery I also may let it stand so till <hi>Elias</hi> commeth, he will teach us at last; the Spirit sayth, The woman which thou hast seene is the great Citty that hath the Dominion over the Kings of the Earth, as I conceive it should be the false Christendome in its Carnal sects: I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that wee should not looke on the external Citty, but on the great Citty, that is, nor on the visible structure of houses, but on the whole Empire, which happily is the great Citty, called <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and this Empire or the Woman which boasteth that shee is chast and not a whore, but God will discover her shame, so that her whoredome shall be knowne to all the world, and the ten Kings which have committed whoredome with her, will hate her and make
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118009:22"/> her desolate, and burne her with fire, and give her kingdome to the Beast till the words of God be accomplished.</p>
               <p>Now whether these ten Kings have already begunne to hate the whore and to lay her waste you may judge, for from heenceforth she shall be still consumed with the fire of the fierce wrath of God both spiritually and bodily, therefore I am of opinion that the great whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> is not onely an externall kingdome, but also a spirituall Woman, and that she is the whore <hi>Jezabel,</hi> which sayth that shee is a Prophetesse, and seduceth the servants of God to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit spirituall whoredome, and to eate of the offerings unto Idols, and so I conceive to be the Woman the wicked Doctrine of which the Prophet speaketh, <hi>Zacha:</hi> 5. and the whore, of which <hi>Solomon</hi> speaketh in his <hi>Proverbs,</hi> that shee inticeth young men to court and play with he, now there is a Prognostication set, <hi>Revel:</hi> 2. 20, 21, 22. &amp;c. <hi>viz:</hi> that the Lord will cast her on the bed of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and her Adulterers also, if they doe not turne from their workes and kill her Children, therefore wee acknowledge a twofold Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonian whore, namely, a spirituall and a worldly one, the one shall be judged with the bodyly sword, and the other with the sword of the Spirit. And that wee may better learne to know the great <hi>Babylon,</hi> and to take notice by her names, what manner of ones shee hath; shee is called <hi>Babel,</hi> a confusion, namely, where the tongues and languages are mixed, where the one cannot understand what the other sayth, nor these two, what the third sayth, and these three cannot understand what the fourth sayth, or what he mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and so they are confounded, nay quite scattered, and at last it is come so farre, so that they have not onely disputed and argued one with another a long time, warring one against another, destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, laying waste and rooting up one another, farre worse then the great <hi>Babylon;</hi> Behold thus have I seene it upon my Watch Tower, and so I tell you of it, happily you may see it as well if you are not blinde yee watchmen on the Tower, <hi>Isa</hi> 56. 10. What doe you thinke now what kinde of people this must be of <hi>Babel,</hi> that wicked great whore, who hath caused all that tumult and stirre like yonder whore <hi>Jezabel,</hi> yet shee paynteth and adorneth her selfe with this and with that, and is hanged about with purple and scarlet, gilded over with gold, Jewells and pearles of the holy Scripture, nay quite with a divine nature, and kingly generation with the Fathers, Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolls and Councells; for thus I have seene her, and as shee was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118009:23"/> shewed unto me so I relate unto you of her, and you will not take it ill of me, and shee hath a Golden Cup in her hand, which is fayre, and all of Gold on the outside, so shee seemes to be, <hi>Math: 7. 25. 2 Corinth:</hi> 11. 13, 14. but within it is full of abomination and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannesse of her whoredome, and is distinct from the Cup of the Prophet <hi>Esdras</hi> as poyson and physicke is, 4 <hi>Esdras</hi> 14. 39. And that you may the better understand what manner of drinke there is in the Cup of the great Babylonian whore, therefore read <hi>Collos: 2. 8. James</hi> 3. 14, 15. and drinke no more out of it, but goe to him that calleth you to the Drinke and Water of Life, <hi>Isaiah 55. Jere: 2. 13. John 4. 14. Psal:</hi> 36. 10. for death and poyson is in the Cup of the great Whore, which is the Heathenish Phylosophy, Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malish Theology and perversnesse in the Civill Law; now out of the Cup of this great Babylonian whore have drunke all Kings and Heathens, and are made so drunke that they reele and fall destroying one another, and lay the whore waste and desolate, thus it is so, and all the World is inebriated with it, therefore doth shee stirre so much also, shee tumbleth, reeleth and falls, <hi>Jerem:</hi> 51. 7. and it is not yet come to the full ripenesse, as you shall feele it by woefull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</p>
               <p>Now the Merchants are much perplext at this fall of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they beginne already to weepe, lament, and howle, which they have done a long time also, and seeke for Remedy here and there, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Babel</hi> might be cured, and to heale the soare, and have fetcht severall playsters, salves, and sweedes, and apply it to the soare, to try whether it may be healed, but it still growes worse, therefore they say wee applyed Cures to <hi>Babylon,</hi> but shee is not healed, wee will leave her, and let every one returne home, for her judgement is come, exalted to heaven and to the Clouds, <hi>Jerem: 51. 9. Revel:</hi> 18. 5. Therefore <hi>Babel</hi> cannot be cured with any salve, playster, and swede, for shee hath the French disease, and hath a soare which eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and corrodeth every part about her, that will suddenly make an end of her; Now seeing that <hi>Babel</hi> the great Citie hath inebriated all the Heathens of her Cup, therefore shee must be punisht there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, wherewith shee hath sinned, namely, both thee and all those that have committed whoredome with her, must now also drinke of the Cup which the Lord hath in his hand, and giveth of it to drinke to all Kings and Heathens, <hi>Jere:</hi> 25. 15. and <hi>Babel</hi> also must drinke, <hi>Revel:</hi> 16. 19. for the Judgement commeth in which the Cup goeth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118009:23"/> about, and of which all wee must drinke even the House of God, and the Citie of God, where the Judgement began, <hi>Jerem: 25. 39. 1 Pet:</hi> 4. 17. but the wicked must drinke of the dreggs and perish thereof, <hi>Psal:</hi> 75. 9. This is the generall Prognostication over all the Inhabitants of the earth, <hi>viz:</hi> that the Judgement commeth, here now is no other Remedy but as the Apostle sayth, 1 <hi>Cor: 11. 31. Acts</hi> 3. 19. Seeing <hi>Babel</hi> must fall be shee never so much under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propped, because her time is come, namely, the great Citie which remaineth over the Kings on the earth, which is not onely the Citie <hi>Rome,</hi> but rather the whole Empire; therefore her Merchants will howle the more here and there and in all places, that her wares will sell no more, and there will be none that will buy them both spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and temporal, especially being false wares and not true Gold and pearles wherewith the Whore hath deckt her selfe as it shall be manifest, for I have seene a Refiner comming which melteth and refineth the Gold and the Silver of the Babylonians with the shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest proofe in the fire through Antymony, there it went away alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Antymony, read of it <hi>Mal:</hi> 3. 3. He hath brought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the Babylonian garments to the fire, even as the pure incomba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stible garment is purged, all is consumed also; Therefore I advise you that you goe out from <hi>Babel,</hi> and from her Merchants, and buy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more approved Gold and Garment of him who adviseth and warneth us least wee be burnt with fire, with the great whore, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel: 3. 18. Chap:</hi> 18. 4. Hee that hath eares let him heare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>The Ninth Chapter. What manner of Prognostication and Nativity is sett for Shepherds and Watchmen, which watch over the fold and flocke, what shall befall them?</head>
               <p>SEeing these men are learned and handle the Scripture, and have with the Pope the keyes to the kingdome of heaven, and have power to open heaven, and shutt it againe, as they suppose, and may save, condemne, and excommunicate men as they beleive, I would
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118009:24"/> not willingly intangle or trouble my selfe with them, however I must discharge my selfe in my office, least I should be found trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous to him that hath sett me in the Tower to keepe Watch, and whereas I am a Watchman amongst others, I hope they will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse me, and I will be very circumspect to speake nothing without Scripture, and nothing but what I have discovered on the Tower. If I consider well the Prognostication and Nativity of these watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I finde and observe that they have not all one ascendent, and every one hath a peculiar or singular Wind in the Head, which is plaine in that, because they are thus scattered more then those at <hi>Corinth, 1 Cor:</hi> 3. 4. Besides there are so many schysmes, so that every one would clime to be a Pope, for the Pope's Ascendent, transcendeth the rest; but I feare the Popes Descendent is come equally with the Popes upon them, <hi>Isa:</hi> 4. 7. because <hi>Elias</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. 18. read the whole Chapter; But if I shall speake of their Nativity, it is found that they are blind and know nothing which is the true Religion, and even the Angel of the Church at <hi>Laodicea, Revel:</hi> 3. 17. which boasteth highly and are so blinde that all the visions of the Prophets are to them as a word of a sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led booke, which if it be given to one for to read it, he replyeth I cannot, for it is sealed, or as if it were given to one that cannot read it, why? because the Lord hath filled to you a spirit, a hard sleepe, and hath shutt your eyes, he hath blinded your Prophets &amp; Princes, together with the Seers, <hi>Isa:</hi> 29. 9, 10. 11, and 12. The Shepherds are become fooles and care not for the Lord, which is the Reason why they can teach no sound Doctrine, all the flockes are scattered, read what the Lord speaketh of the Prophet, <hi>Jere:</hi> 23. it is a hard Prognostication but it is very true, it is much if it be well conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all Heards are scattered, for the one is this, the other is that, the one hath or is of such a faith and Religion, which is in the right, and which is in the wrong? <hi>Math: 24. 23, 24, 25. Luke</hi> 17. 23. and who shall determine it? Christ the true Shepherd and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge sayth <hi>Luke 18. 8. Doest thou thinke that the Sonne of man will finde faith on Earth at his comming?</hi> What doe you thinke of this saying, surely they may make ones hayre stand staring upright, nay the Lord sayth yet more, <hi>Math: 24. 24. If it were possible the very Elect may be seduced unto Errors;</hi> But that holds still; <hi>Who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiveth our preaching, and to whom is the Arme of the Lord now knowne?</hi> Isaiah 53. Now because no man dareth to give the Lord
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118009:24"/> the lye, therefore the Word of God standeth firme and holds, as it is written, <hi>God is onely true and all men are lyars,</hi> amongst whom I count my selfe engeniously to be the greatest, <hi>Rom:</hi> 3. 4. least any should thinke I counted my selfe more righteous then other men are. What will become of all these severall and various Religions and disputings, may it not be learned and knowne? Yes, for I see one comming in the forme and similitude of a Prophet, having a Scepter in his hand, and a two edged sword girt by his side, out of his mouth commeth a consuming fiery Flame; having an open book in his left hand, he goeth to this great multitude that have worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the golden Calfe, saying with a loud and great voyce, Come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to me yee that belong to the Lord, there gathered unto him the Children of <hi>Levi,</hi> which are spoken of, <hi>Mala:</hi> 3. 3. who are purifyed by the melter and refiner, and he sayd, <hi>Girt every man his sword by his side, and goe in and out from gate to gate throughout the Campe, and slay every man his brother, and every man his companion, and every man his Neighbour, and the Children of Levi did according to the word of Moses, and there fell of the people that day about three thousand Men,</hi> Exod: 32. 25. &amp;c. What signifyeth this vision? <hi>Remember yee the Law of Moses my servant, which I commanded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in Horeb for all Israel the statutes and judgements,</hi> Mala: 4. 4. Now because I have seene all this on my Guard and on the Mount, therefore I must Prognosticate Warre and the sword to you Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds and Watchmen, namely, the sword of the Lord, which shall warre with you, and this sword is called the word of God, which you much boast of, of which you may read, <hi>Revel: 2. 16. Chap: 16. 1. Chap: 19. 13. 15. Heb:</hi> 4. 12. and that you may yet better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it, Read, <hi>Ephes: 6. 17. 2 Thess: 2. 8. Isaiah 11. 4. Zach:</hi> 4. 6. Now if you joyntly in your Multitude can defend your selves against one Man, you may try, I feare you are not able, the Reason is, because you doe not agree amongst your selves, you are too much divided, and so you are the easier overcome, and yee are not able to stand against that one; Therefore I have seene one comming from or in the North, whose comming out is from the East, on which is written the name of the Lord, which is called <hi>Elias,</hi> he knoweth not your Names, and beareth the Name of the Lord in his mouth, he was compassed with all manner of sects which he cut in peices in the name of the Lord, <hi>Psal:</hi> 118. and trampled the <hi>Saganim</hi> under foote, even as a Potter treadeth his Loame, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 41. 25. And I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118009:25"/> have seene also that the Lord hath trod Satan under his feete, and no man could hinder it; I have seene also that three Greyhounds which belonged to the Hangman, rann all at him to teare him in peices, but God tooke him up on high in a moment, even when the Hounds snatcht at him; and I saw three other Doggs stand before him, which fayne would have had a fling at him, but he had an Axe in his hand which frighted the Doggs away, and a flocke of sheepe stood before him which he was to feed.</p>
               <p>What other Prognostication shall I shew unto you Shepherds, but that you also must drinke of the Cup, of which <hi>Jere:</hi> 25. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied; for thus sayth the Lord, <hi>ver: 34. Howle yee Shepherds, and Cry and wallow your selves in the ashes yee chiefe of the flocke; for the dayes of your slaughter and of your dispersions are accomplished, and yee shall fall like a precious vessell, and the Shepherds shall have no way to flee, nor the principal of the flocke to escape; a voyce of the Cry of the Shepherds, and an howling of the cheife of the Flocke shall be heard, for the Lord hath spoyled their pasture, and the peaceable inhabitants are cutt downe because of the fierce Anger of the Lord. Hee hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken his Covert, as the Lyon, for their Land is desolate because of the oppressour, and because of his fierce anger.</hi> What doe yee thinke yee Shepherds, have you found any of it come to passe? All is nothing to that which is yet to come; for now commeth the sword of the Spirit which separateth soule and spirit, he with his Anatomizing will make such a section by the Anatomist, that all shall be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and nothing shall be covered, and indeed with such a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation the like thereof was never done, since the world was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and never the like shall be done any more, <hi>Heb:</hi> 4. 12, 13. Remember the Act and the sword of the great Prophet <hi>Elias, 1 Kings</hi> 18. none shall escape this two edged sword, let him be mounted as high as he will, though he be as high as the Pope at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet the time is come that he which exalted himselfe so high, and hath even seated himselfe in Gods place must come downe, all hills and Mountaines shall be humbled and levelled, and the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes shall be exalted, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 2. 40. Rugged, rough and uneven things shall be layd flatt and made plaine, because he commeth which shall bring all things to Right, and the glory of the Lord shall be revealed, that all flesh shall see that the Mouth of the Lord speaketh, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 52. 6. What will come out of it at the last? that which is written, <hi>Math:</hi> 24. 14. of which more hath been spoken
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118009:25"/> above, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord himselfe will take care of his flocke, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them at their hands, and will visit his sheep in grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and will give to them onely one Shepherd, which shall make one fold out of Christians and Jewes, <hi>Chap:</hi> 37. 16. Read this Chapter unto the end. And wee all shall have one onely Shepherd, namely, that good Shepherd, who hath layd downe his life for his sheepe, and he will gather all the flockes into one fold, and sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Goates from the sheepe on the day of Judgement, and give unto them their Reward, and there will be one flocke and one Shepherd, <hi>John</hi> 10. This joyfull good newes and happy Prognosti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation should stirre us up to be glad and cheerefull, and render thankes unto the Lord, because the time is now come in which he will gather his faithfull and select people from the foure Winds, and from the End of the Earth, through the shrill trumpet of the Gospel of the kingdome, <hi>Math:</hi> 24. 14. 31. Then the righteous shall shine like the Sunne in the kingdome of their father, <hi>Chap:</hi> 13. 43. He that hath eares to heare let him heare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>The Tenth Chapter. What kinde of Prognosticke and Nativity shall be sett for Ʋniversities, and other Schooles, for Doctors, Chayre-men, Masters, Students, Writers, Printers, Stationers?</head>
               <p>IT is to be admired what Nativity the Apostle appropriateth to such men when he sayth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7. The end and scope of the Commandement is, <hi>Charity, out of a pure heart and a good Conscience, and of fayth unfayned;</hi> whereas some of them have erred, they turned to unprofitable Babling, they will be teachers of the Scripture, and yet understand not what they say, nor what they should hold, or confirme; that is to say, themselves know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be right or wrong, true or false, and so dispute still about it, even to this time, and their day for disputing is Saterday or Sunnes Eve, if they knew it, what need to dispute about it, why they doe not keepe to the summe held forth by the Apostle in this now quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118009:26"/> place? Therefore the Apostle sayth againe, 2 <hi>Tim: 3. 7. They are alwayes learning, and cannot attaine unto the knowledge of truth,</hi> nay they rather oppose the truth, like as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood <hi>Moses,</hi> and they are such men who are corrupt in their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, and cannot examine saith neither doe they know what true Faith and Religion is, and yet will never leave off disputing, every one thinking himselfe in the right; but they shall proceed no further, for their folly shall be revealed to all, even as the others were made knowne unto the world; This is one thing which is prognosticated unto them, namely, that their foolishnesse shall be publickly made knowne, and indeed not long ester these dayes; for I have seene this Revelation with my eyes on my watch Tower, and indeed to speake it in one word, because they doe not know themselves, and doe not know once what man is, and so as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture it will befall them as it did <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> who was a cheife Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and Master in <hi>Israel,</hi> who understood not earthly matters, what should he know of the heavenly things! <hi>John</hi> 3. Nay if there were but so much goodnesse in them as to come with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> to Christ by night, and conferre with the onely Master about matters. Now because they cannot agree among themselves, and their senses are scattered, in Theologicall as well as Philosophicall matters, and yet still dispute whether Logick be an Ens, an Art, an habit, &amp;c. and it is manifest also in themselves that they belong to <hi>Babel,</hi> therefore the Nativity and Prognosticke of the great whore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> will light upon them also: and it is needlesse to make any great dispute about it, for the appells doe not fall farre off from the Tree, and this is our naturall principle, namely, from whence a thing commeth, thither it returnes; This Maxime alone exceeds farre and is more Real then their whole <hi>Aristotle,</hi> then all their Physicks and Metaphysicks, and all their Philosophy, would to God that all they both Philosophers and Divines might but observe this one Axioma, they would learne more in one moment, then they have learned in many hundred and thousand yeares, from hence generally proceeds all Ignorance, because they have no principles, neither have they seene or knowne what thing a Principle is; seeing they have not true principles neither in the one nor in the other Faculty or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, or what you may call it; Therefore themselves know not from whence they are, and whither they returne, in regard they are ignorant of this Maxim or Theorema (to wit) from whence a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118009:26"/> thing is, thither it returneth; to this Axiome of Wisdome, <hi>viz:</hi> from whence a thing is, thither it returneth, the onely Master hath proposed unto us <hi>John</hi> 3. and there also <hi>John the Baptist;</hi> God knoweth that I wish it from the bottome of my heart, that you all might observe it well, and consider it diligently, and meditate onely on this word, then you might easily be helped, and you would not have need hereafter to make use of Bookes in your Studyes, in all your faculties, onely this one, which is the Word of God; I would not have you thinke that I despise you, or doe not wish you well, God forbid but I doe it for your good, I would not that you should run on any further into perdition. Therefore I give to you a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full warning, according to the duty of my place, and I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded as a Watchman so to doe; for the word is, <hi>To the Law and to the Testimony;</hi> ought not the people to aske and inquire of his God? <hi>Isaiah</hi> 8. 19, 20. But now your Wisdome is not from above, and out of God, but from below, and out of the flesh, of which you may read, <hi>James</hi> 3. 14, 15. Not because I say it, but that I have thus seene and heard it of him that commeth after me, of whom I am not worthy to make cleane the shooes of one of his Prophets; Tomorrow is the Sun-day <hi>Judica,</hi> where wee read in the Gospel for that day, that Christ sayth <hi>John 8. 46, 47. If I tell you the truth, why doe you not beleive me? He that is of God heareth Gods word;</hi> It may well be called <hi>Judica,</hi> for there is a mighty heavy Judgement comming even over you, Universities, Doctors, Chayre-men, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and over all that belongeth thereunto this I tell you; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judge once a righteous Judgement, and no more after the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of men <hi>John</hi> 7. 24. Perhaps God may be gracious unto you, but all ignorance commeth from thence, because the Word of God is not regarded, and you thinke not that any Physicks can be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Bible, of which it doth so abound, even as a Fountaine which springeth continually as well in the New as in the old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if wee had onely eyes to see and to draw the Water, and the Lying Spirit hath perswaded these book-men, that, that, which is true in Phylosophy, to be false in Theology, and that which is true in Theology does not hold in Phylosophy it is truer, namely, in your Phylosophy, and your Theology; <hi>Quae qualis quanta sit, qui post me venit vobis monstrabit.</hi> Yee Book-men, what have yee acted and driven on one among another so many hundred and thousand yeares with all your Preaching, Reading, Teaching Crying and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118009:27"/> Scribling, and you have filled the World full of Bookes, which are endlesse and numberlesse, nothing else but that you thereby are more and more scattered, confused, and intricated; and this is the Prognosticke upon all your Bookes which wee Read <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 19. Namely, your Shop will be burnt with fire, both bodily and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually. Then the shopmen of <hi>Babel</hi> shall howle weepe, and lament, <hi>Revel:</hi> 18. 8. 11. because no body will buy their wares any more. How doe you like this Prognosticke you Letter-Casters, Composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Setters, Printers and Stationers; and indeed the Scripture sayth, <hi>all this shall come to passe in one Day and in one houre,</hi> Revel: 18. 17. 19. Now I know full well that you will not beleive it, but you will finde it too true, and sooner then you looke for, especially when the Gospel of the kingdome shall be preached all the world over. True there are many scorners, mockers and despisers in the world, even so were they from the beginning, and every one is secure; there is no end of Building and Planting, of Marrying and Dancing, of sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and buying, of gormandizing and Tipling, because the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie of Christ must be fullfilled <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 26. &amp;c. and he that speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of it is mocked and derided and despised for it; therefore it will come upon them, as it is written in their Prognosticke, <hi>Mala: 4. Isaiah</hi> 28. What will become of it seeing all this buisnesse of Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men shall goe to wrack come to an end, and shall be burnt with fire, Namely, this will come of it, the Bookes which hitherto have been sealed shall be opened, and those which hitherto have been open, shall be shutt, of which read, <hi>Isaiah 33. 4. 4 Esdras 6. 20. Revel:</hi> 6. 12, 13, 14. And properly the true meaning of it is this, That wee shall be all taught of God, and none shall teach the other any more, and say, Know the Lord, for they shall all know him, from the least to the greatest, because God will powre forth his Spirit upon all flesh, and write his Law in our hearts and be gracious unto us all, and then the whole Earth also will be filled with the knowledge of God, of this you may read, <hi>Isaiah 11. 9. Chap:</hi> 29 24. and 32. 4. and 35. 8. and 52. 6. and 54. 13. <hi>Jere: 2. 15, Chap:</hi> 24. 7. and 31. 33, 34. <hi>Ezek: 36. 25, 26, 27. Item 11. 19. Jere: 32. 29. Joel 2. 28. Zacha:</hi> 12. 10.</p>
               <p>Who would not rejoyce from the bottome of his heart because there is such a happinesse at hand which all shall enjoy, the children of God, and all those which call upon the Name of the Lord, and all those which goe out from <hi>Babel,</hi> and those that confesse and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118009:27"/> their blindnesse, darknesse, and sinne, and pray to God for Grace and illumination, as I being warned and taught of God have done and that one may be taught gratis, not to spend a penny on it, when hitherto so great expences were made for to be learned, and to goe to this and that Schoole for it whereas now a body may sit at home, set not one foote out of Doores, <hi>Isai: 55. Rom: 10. 6, 7, 8. Luke</hi> 17. 21. 23. Therefore be advised <hi>Laodicea,</hi> that you also may be helped, <hi>Revel:</hi> 3. 4. &amp;c. Therefore he that will heare let him heare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>The Eleventh Chapter. What shall be Prognosticated for Physitians and Surgeons, Apothecaries, and Chymists, Miners, and the like.</head>
               <p>TO what miseries, calamities, and lamentable distractions mans life is subject unto, even from the Mothers wombe to the Grave, none knoweth better then poore sicke and weakly men, for which are ordained Physitians, Apothecaries, and such like, and there is no calling and profession on Earth which is more necessary and usefull for man, next unto the Apostolicke and propheticall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, then Physicke, and if one had all the world, and were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther happy nor healthy, what would it profit a man, and this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession hath a good Testimony, not onely in the holy Scripture, <hi>Exod: 13. 26. Syrach</hi> 38 1, 2. &amp;c. but also in the experience, be it what it will; The Physitians will also have an End, so will their Apothecaries, Surgeons, and the like, have a Rest from their cares and paines, And let them take this for their Prognostication, from my watch Tower that I have heard, but not yet seene, namely, that there shall come such an universall Medicine, which not onely cureth all diseases, and preserveth health, but shall take Death quite away, and swallow him eternally, what could a man wish for more in this world then for this; Because Death raigneth over all, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Christ dyed, arose againe, and ascended into heaven, and sitteth at the right hand of God, what was it to poore men at the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118009:28"/> Time of Christ and his Apostles, that they were delivered by them from so many infirmities, and healed of them? Christ his Apostles and Prophets had this profession, and therefore it is more worthy then others, and is next to the Propheticall calling, and one might wonder why uncivill Lawyers should take the upper hand of Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, doe these unexpert men not know that health is better then Riches and Goods? But that you might not thinke as if I had told a Fable concerning the universall Medicine, you shall understand my Prognosticke thus of the Right and true universall Medicine, which will be not onely for man, but for all flesh, namely, there stands a Tree, and it is in Paradize, which is called the Tree of Life, which shall be revealed and made knowne at the glorious and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full comming of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, whose fruit shall be plucked and eaten, whereby all men and all flesh shall be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and freed from death, and that so really and fundamentally and certainly, as really as at the Beginning of the fall into sinne through the plucking of the forbidden fruite and the eating thereof, wee and all flesh are fallen into sinne and Death, and are come into all mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and necessity. Now God hath reserved this glory and transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Joy for us the last, and reserved the good Wine till now, even at these our times, all and what hitherto hath been concealed shall be revealed, be it never so secret and mysticall, so now also shall the way to the Tree of Life be Revealed, which time the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> calls the times of Refreshings from the presence of the Lord, and the times of Restitution, all what was lost or taken away in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 19, 20, 21. At which the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> poynteth, <hi>Chap</hi> 9. 24. Wee read of the great Apostle, how he was Ravished into Paradize, where he heard unspeakeable words, which is not lawfull for a man to speake, <hi>Of such a one I will glory,</hi> saith he, 2 <hi>Corinth:</hi> 12. 4. What words should these be? I poore wretch am farre inferior to St <hi>Paul,</hi> and why should any thought come into my heart as to know what it was, however in the feare of the Lord I may very well say, that this which I shall tell I have heard of the glory of the Children of God which is revealed unto me, of the which all other creatures with us shall pertake, which hitherto have waited for with a longing and sighing desire, <hi>Rom: 8. ver:</hi> 19, 20, 21. Read also 4 <hi>Esdras 7. v: 53. Chap: 8. v:</hi> 52, 53, 54. But when <hi>Elias</hi> commeth who was with Christ on the Mount, he shall speake to you more of it. Now wee tell you thus as wee have heard of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118009:28"/> Tree of Life, which hitherto was sealed, and no man either durst or could breake that seale, because a fiery Mountaine lyeth before it, which shall not be removed unlesse Christ come with great power and glory, of whose comming wee speake to you that it is nearer at hand then is beleived of men. Being it is so therefore I have such a Prognostication to all Physitians that their Medicines will be worth nothing then, because another Garden is found out, of which shall and may be gathered and fetched not onely the hearb unto health, but against the very death also, who should not rejoyce for you also shall be made partaker of it, if you accept of and beleive it, and my Prognostication be not contrary and against you.</p>
               <p>Moreover, let the Chymists know and have this prognosticke from Me, namely, that the Philosophers Stone, wherewith they have cured the sicke, their universall and highest Medicine will be worth nothing then neither, and is farre inferior to this universall Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, of which I have heard and doe tell you of it, and will be more inferior, then Water in respect of the other; What doe you thinke of it you that prate so much of Chymicke Matters, and have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten so many bookes of it, and have perplexed and involved many therewith? I doe not speake of the true and solid Alchymists, who besides are found Good Christians, but the sadlers and quacks which however were serviceable to their neighbour with a plaine singlenesse of heart; As Fryer <hi>Basilius Valentinus, Theophrastus,</hi> and others, these also shall heare this Word, I have been sicke and you have visited me, and looked not alwayes for your fee and pay, as such Money-Physitians for the most part doe, and forget Mercy and Love, and are not Samaritans; Therefore you Alchymists must know, that all your glory will have an end as well of the universall Medicine as of the projection &amp; transmutation of Mettalls inferior, to turne them into Gold or Silver, and this out of the Earth. Glory shall come to Miners that they will bring in the new World out of the Earth, more Gold and Silver then there will be need or use for, and that shall be cleare and pure and compact not needing to be melted or refined, or have you not read the Prognostication of it, <hi>Isaîah</hi> 60. 17. No man is able to beleive what transcendent and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundant Treasures and Riches in the Mountaines doe lye hid, nay plainly on the earth, and on the Acres, and the feilds of Gold and Silver and pretious Stones, which hitherto was hidden and sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led till the last time, in which all shall be Revealed unto the praise
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118009:29"/> of God, but what is that on the earth in respect of that which is in Paradice, and what is that in Paradice in comparison to that glory which is in the divine World? for there is a thing more noble and higher then the Tree of Life in Paradice, namely, the Stone which the Builders hitherto have rejected, <hi>Psal:</hi> 118. Many will thinke now whither will this goe at last, If I knew onely to make the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers Stone, or where these Treasures lye hid, of which you speake, I could willingly leave the other subtill speculations unto thee, not to he that seeketh meerely corruptible things will perish with them, this is a true Prognostication, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 17. But he that seeketh before all things, the kingdome of God, him God will seeke also, and make him rich eternally, therefore I doe wish from the bottome of my heart, that all yee were minded as I am, then wee should soone grow and be rich, and inrich others also, I desire no more then from hand to mouth, with my small number I could be rich easily and be in great respect before the World, if I would but worship their God, of which I say thus, Get thee hence Satan, and who should thinke that I should not have a six pence to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow it on a Fish, and to eate it with my Children, which I first must goe and borrow it; O man! if thou didst but know the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundant Riches of the knowledge of Christ Jesus, and of his kingdome and glory, surely thou wouldst say to this World, its Riches and glory; Fye on thee, and Remember what S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> sayth, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3. 7, 8. But now oh man this glory is revealed unto thee, and that gratis, for nothing, you need not give any thing for it, and the Gospel of the kingdome shall be preached in all the world, to all Nations meerely gratis, it is well for him which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges it, and accepteth of the same thankfully, but he that despiseth and rejecteth it, shall in like manner be rejected and despised.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:118009:29"/>
               <head>The Twelfth Chapter. What shall be Prognosticated to the Politicians, Lawyers, Civilians, all rich wicked and unrighteous persons, effeminate men, and the like?</head>
               <p>THe great difference among men and the sonnes of men, must be observed not onely by their names, but rather by their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, otherwise wee shall be deceived by their gay garments, and Sheeps-cloaths. Now these Sheeps-cloaths are so common now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes that wee can hardly know to whom it should belong and be fitting to weare, yet Christ ascribeth the same to the false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Math:</hi> 7. 15. and warneth us that wee should take heed and beware of them, <hi>Math:</hi> 7. 15. But the Foxes furred Coate Christ applyed to King <hi>Herod,</hi> Luk: 13 32. Thereby ought wee to observe what Nativity is due to the Politicians, Lawyers, and the like persons. Now the sheepe, a plaine simple silly harmlesse beast, which taketh paines for his food, and is contented with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and is to be admired, no untowardnesse in it, however it hath three shrewd Enemies, The Lyon, the Wolfe, and the Dogge, or the Lyon Beare, and Wolfe. The sheepe is an Emblem of a poore domesticke state or Husbandman, he must seeke for his bread in the sweat of his browes, but cannot quietly enjoy it, but is tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and plagued, especially at these times, in so much that he very well might wish himselfe out of the world, however Deliverance is not farre off, however there are yet two if not three stormy tempestuous seasons at hand.</p>
               <p>Now there are severall beasts which teare poore men in peices, and are ready to devoure them quite, and lye in waite in their denns for them; such fellows Nativities are exprest in the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Psalme; among these severall Beasts are the Herodian Foxes, the Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Civilians, Lawyers, these are those Foxes, they can be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise named, then Christ and the holy Scripture termed them,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118009:30"/> so that a Fox and they stand together in one predicament, for all crafts, daubing, cunningnesse is concenterated therein. <hi>Aesop</hi> in his Fables setts them out also; the Logicians Rule here holdeth, A Fox is a good Politician and Lawyer, and that a Politician and a Lawyer is a Fox, if it be not so commonly understood, yet it is felt the more. Wherein then does consist this so highly and large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out set Jurisprudentia and politia? doth there belong such a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume to it; must there be so many Lawes? Answer; Whither wee be Heathens or Christians, it matters not; The judgement of these Lawes is this, <hi>Matth: 17. 12. What ever you would have done unto you, you must doe the same to another:</hi> Hee that does not practise this Rule is no good Lawyer, and is unworthy of the name; Now whereas unrighteousnesse hath prevailed too much, and Charitie is quite frozen, and Politicians and Lawyers care not for that stale Rule, although it stands stamped in their owne hearts and consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, <hi>Rom:</hi> 2. 14, 15. but have and make new subtill inventions, therefore wee found a Prognostication for them also, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 10. 1, 2, 3, 4. it is thus, they also shall be destroyed, <hi>Item,</hi> Chap: 5. 20. They are called the Inventors of the Law, which turne Right into Gall, and the fruite of Righteousnesse into Wormewood, <hi>Amos</hi> 5. 7. and <hi>Chap:</hi> 6. 12. read the whole 5 and 6 Chapters: Thus is your whole Prognostication set downe, <hi>Wis:</hi> 6. A good Politician and a good Lawyer, are good Christians also, and be sought after as if they were Gods to give advice, to comfort and helpe, as it is written also, <hi>Psal: 8. 6. Exod:</hi> 22. 8. 28. Such Politicians and Lawyers will be made pertakers also of the kingdome of Christ and of his glory.</p>
               <p>But what is Prognosticated to the Rich, which have gotten Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches by Covetousnesse (which with them is called Gods blessing) oppression, extorsion, &amp;c. <hi>Amos 8. Isal:</hi> 5. 8. Thus speakes Saint <hi>James 5. v: 1. Goe to now yee rich men, weepe and howle for your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series that shall come upon you; your Riches are corrupted, and your Garments moth-eaten; your Gold and Silver is cankered, and the Rust of them shall be a witnesse against you, and shall eate your flesh, as it were fire; you have reaped treasure together for the last dayes, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore many of the Rich covetous men which hitherto have beene so secure, shall heare the voyce of God; <hi>Thou Foole, this night thy soule shall be taken away from thee, and then whose shall
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118009:30"/> all that be which thou hast so greedily gathered,</hi> Luk. 12. 20. Christ sayth, <hi>Chap: 6. 24. Woe unto you that are rich, for yee have received your consolation.</hi> Now as covetousnesse is the roote of all evill, so it shall receive also an ill reward, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 10. and truely he that studyeth to be rich knitteth a snare for himselfe, or maketh a Roape to be hanged therewith, and pulled by into hell; as <hi>Judas Iscariot</hi> did; and in the 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> verse the Apostle calleth <hi>Riches a snare;</hi> and this Prognostication also is sett upon Rich men, that it is very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult for a Rich man to enter into the kingdome of Heaven, <hi>Math:</hi> 19, 23, 24. for all that the whole world striveth to be Rich, and all men are greedy after moneys in their states, <hi>Isaiah 56. 11. Jerem:</hi> 6 13. and if a man be never so Rich, yet will he not say that he hath enough, but who is it that desireth to be Rich in God, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 21. which Christ commanded wee should doe, <hi>Math:</hi> 6. 19, 20, 21. But who Beleiveth this word? But the Prognosticke of the poore is full of Comfort, for the kingdome of Heaven and Salvation is assigned for them, <hi>Math: 5. 3. Luke</hi> 6. 20. What manner of poore men? they are Rich in faith, saith the Scripture, <hi>James</hi> 2. 5. Christ describeth them, that they forsake all for his sake, <hi>Math: 19. 27. Mark: 10. 29, 30. Luke</hi> 14. 26. 33. Now those which choose rather to be poore in this world then to be Rich, they are Rich in faith, for they looke not on that which is visible, but on things invisible, though the world counteth it foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishnesse, 2 <hi>Corinth:</hi> 4. 18.</p>
               <p>What shall wee say or Prognosticate for effeminate and volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous men, which fare deliciously and gallantly in this world? their Nativity is sett downe, <hi>Wisd:</hi> 2. and their Prognostication is in the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Chap: and besides the Scripture speakes plainely, 1 <hi>Cor: 6. 10. Ʋnrighteous men cannot inherit the kingdome of God, nor Theeves, nor Covetous, nor drunkards, nor Revilers,</hi> but if they purge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of all these things, repent sincerely, and feare God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive the Gospel of the kingdome, then they may be saved, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the kingdome of God. Now all these which love the world, eye pleasures, carnall lusts, and a proud life, shall not inherit the kingdome of God, this is their Prognostication, that as the things of this world doe perish, and at last the world also, so they also pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 16, 17. And where man hath his Treasure, there is his heart also, and as his Treasure is, so is his heart, <hi>Math:</hi> 6. 20,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118009:31"/> 21. <hi>viz:</hi> Either corruptible or incorruptible, earthly or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, below on earth or above in heaven, and what every one seeketh or striveth for, the same he shall obtaine, and either will rejoyce in the same together, or else be eternally tormented, <hi>Collos:</hi> 3. 2. But wee doe not looke upon that which is visible and corruptible, but on that which is invisible and eternall, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4. 18.</p>
               <p>In the Closing of this our Prognostication, that every one may know what he shall doe in the last heavie troublesome dangerous times, to escape and avoyd all these miseries prognosticated in this Almanack, and enjoy all good promised therein, and may enter also into the kingdome of heaven. The Apostle giveth a direction here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38, 39. and <hi>Chap:</hi> 3. 19, 20, 21. that wee must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to reject evill and choose the good, <hi>Deut:</hi> 30. 19. and that wee may easily know and conceive what manner of men these are to whom Christ assigneth and admitteth them to his kingdome, <hi>Matth:</hi> 25. 24. Namely, to those who fedd him in his members when they were hungry and thirsty, if it 'twas but a cup of cold water, it shall be rewarded, which is a singular moving word, <hi>Chap. 10. 42. Item</hi> those that have entertained and cloathed him when he was naked, and visited him in his sicknesse and imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but those which doe not so are rejected of Christ, therefore shew mercy and you shall receive mercy, <hi>Math: 5. 7. Luke</hi> 6. 36. therefore no other conclusion and sentence but this, <hi>Those that have done good shall enter into life, and those that have done evill shall enter into death and damnation,</hi> John 5. 29. <hi>for Judgement shall be kept answerable to every mans worke,</hi> Matth: 7. 21. Revel: 2. 23. Rom: 2. <hi>Therefore as man soweth, so shall he reape, be it good or bad,</hi> Gal: 6. 7, 8, 9, 10. And this is our generall Prognostication wherewith wee conclude,</p>
               <q>Behold I come as a Theife in the Night, Blessed is he that watcheth and keepeth his Garments, that he walke not naked, and his nakednesse be seene.</q>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118009:31"/>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Finished through the grace and helpe of the Spirit, <date>on Saturday before the Sunday of <hi>Judica</hi> being the 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> day of <hi>Aprill Anno</hi> 1647.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Quasi per posta Postilion.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:118009:32"/>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:118009:32"/>
            <head>Conclusion.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE may well say at our times that wee are in a perverse world, even as it was in the times of</hi> Noah, <hi>of</hi> Lott, <hi>and of</hi> Christ, <hi>of which</hi> Christ <hi>saith,</hi> Luke 7. 31, 32. With whom shall I compare this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and to what are they like; they are like to Children sitting in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place, calling one to another, saying, Wee have piped unto you, and you have not danced, wee have mourned unto you, and yee have not wept; <hi>Even so it is in this perverse world in this our time; Wee have many yeares since, from</hi> Anno 1619. <hi>tould publickly both of a Good and of a bad time, that was at hand, but all was derided and Calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, so that they would beleive or receive neither good nor bad; But the Holy Scripture tould thus much aforehand,</hi> That in the last dayes there will be scoffers, that walke after their owne lusts, saying, Where is the promise of his comming, 2 <hi>Pet: 3. 3, 4. And the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel saith to</hi> Daniel, Chap: 12. 10. Wicked men will doe wickedly, and will not regard it, <hi>namely, they will not search into the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the lust time; but the understanding and Judicious man will Inquire into; Therefore Christ compareth these last times, with the times of</hi> Noah, <hi>and of</hi> Lott, Math: 24. 37, 38. Luke 17. 26, 27, 28. <hi>which ought to be observed by reason of the great securitie which was in the times of</hi> Noah, <hi>and of</hi> Lot, <hi>even to the day in which the fire and water came, and tooke them all away; Even so it is in our time, and no other, and indeed the Watch men in</hi> Israel <hi>are most secure, and it is just with them as the Prophet told, let us eate and drinke, and have good dayes, as it is to day, so shall it be to morow,</hi> &amp;c. Isaiah the 56. 10, 11, 12. <hi>And if a poore man comes and tells them of any thing, then they brand him with the name of</hi> a new Prophet, Enthusiast,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118009:33"/> Phantast, <hi>and</hi> Millenary, <hi>nay they presume to say, that he is a Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger of the Devill, and turne him out of Doore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus the Watch men in</hi> Israel <hi>doe, and which are drunke, and fall along, therefore the</hi> 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Chapter of</hi> Isaiah <hi>will come on them, as sure as it is written, and the</hi> 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Chapter of</hi> Malachy, <hi>where unto wicked men and scoffers is denounced a fiery Furnance; as also</hi> Thess: 2. <hi>the 1. 8. Carelesse ignorant secure men prate of a Peace in our times, but how much they will misse of it, the duple</hi> Quinarius <hi>will prove it at his comming after few dayes. Seeing there is no remedy for this perverse world, therefore God will deale with them accordingly,</hi> Psal. 18. 17. <hi>And will sweepe them away with the beesom of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Isaiah <hi>the</hi> 14<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. 23. <hi>Nothing shall prevaile against, though</hi> Moses <hi>and</hi> Samuel <hi>should stand and intreate for them,</hi> Jere: 15. <hi>And the</hi> Postilion <hi>amongst other things, brings the</hi> 7<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Chapter of</hi> Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, <hi>which must be read from the beginning to the end, and the</hi> 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Chapter also, for those which mourne and sigh over the abominations that are committed in</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>shall be marked and sealed,</hi> Revel: 2. <hi>Therefore the destroying Angel shall be loosed after the yeare of</hi> Libra, <hi>to destroy the third part of men,</hi> Chap: 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> and 15. <hi>and then will be no sparing, and though these should dwell all in one Citie, yet they shall not be able to marry, neither their sonnes nor daughters, but onely the Lord will have a Care over them, by reason of their righteousnesse,</hi> Ezek: 14. v: 13. 16. <hi>Therefore the Spirit of Prophecy Concludeth thus,</hi> Revel: 22. 11. Hee that is unjust, let him be unjust still, and hee that is filthy, let him be filthy still, and hee that is righteous, let him be righteous still, and behold, I come quickly, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is with me, to give every man according as his worke shall be.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="by_the_same_author">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:118009:33"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of all the Bookes of this Authour, that are partly Printed, and not Printed.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Chronology or Computation of the yeares of the World, Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1617. After which at this yeare 1655. the World may be told, 5885.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Spectulum Temporis;</hi> The Glasse of time.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Christianus Christianum,</hi> that is, the simple Christendome, held forth in seven Questions, Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1624. 1629. 1630.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>Chilias Sancta,</hi> of the 1000 yeares as the time of the Sabboth, and of the Conversion of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and their Returne into their owne Country; of three sheetes. 1625.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>Aurora Sapientiae,</hi> The dawning of Wisdome, 1628, 1629.</item>
               <item>6. The Mystery of the Temple of the Lord, in three parts, 1630.</item>
               <item>7. The Glasse of Wisdome and Truth, together with a Missive to the Shepherds and sheepe. 1631.</item>
               <item>8. The Glasse of Monarchs in three parrs. 1633.</item>
               <item>9. <hi>Apologia Christiano,</hi> in 7<seg rend="sup">o</seg> Poynt of the Person of Christ. 1639.</item>
               <item>10. The Treatise called <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. The booke of <hi>Jehi,</hi> Or a dawning of light. 1640.</item>
               <item>12. <hi>Harmonia Sapientiae,</hi> The unitie of Wisdome. 1647.</item>
               <item>13. <hi>Sphera Sapientiae,</hi> The Circle of Wisdome. 1650.</item>
               <item>14. <hi>Theantupologia,</hi> A speech concerning Humanity. 1650.</item>
               <item>15. A Treatise concerning the Lords Supper. 1650.</item>
               <item>16. The Glasse of Baptisme, and its Mystery. 1651.</item>
               <item>17. <hi>Mysterium Magnum,</hi> of the Great Mystery of Christ and his Church. 1651.</item>
               <item>18. <hi>Informatarium Catecheticum,</hi> a Catechisme of Faith unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, together with a little Childrens Postill, and some Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. 1652.</item>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118009:34"/>
               <item>19. <hi>Perspicillium Bellicum,</hi> Warres Perspective. 1652.</item>
               <item>20. Examen or Christians defence about the Person of Christ. 1653.</item>
               <item>21. <hi>Lucer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Sapientiae,</hi> a Lampe of Light of Wisdome, dedicated to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>onated <hi>Socinians.</hi> 1654.</item>
               <item>22. <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at is, Parting, Judgement, and Promise of beleife, and Misbeleife, dedicated to those of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> in all Humaine sects. 1654.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>These following Bookes are given to be Printed.</head>
               <item>1. <hi>BOnum nuntium Israeli,</hi> Good tydings to <hi>Israel</hi> of the three signes of the Comming of Christ, dedicated to <hi>Rabbi Menosse Ben: Israele,</hi> in <hi>Amsterdam</hi> in Latine.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Percipicillium Theologicum,</hi> or an Examen of such which would be seene, and love to be called Divines, with an answer to a booke called, <hi>To the Law and to the Testimony.</hi> The Authour is <hi>Adam Burrell,</hi> in Latine.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Examen Photianianorum,</hi> an answer to all the Arguments which <hi>John Crellius</hi> the Socinian made of the One and True God, in Latine.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>Stella vespertina,</hi> Evening Starre of the Nativity of Principles, Elements, Mineralls and Mettalls, and their signatures.</item>
               <item>5. Harmony of Faith and Religion, that is, have all Humaine sects together with the Jewes, Turkes and Pagans, may easily be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to one Knowledge, Faith, and Religion, and be Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God and Christ.</item>
               <item>6. Postilion, or An Astrologicall Propheticall Prognostication, wherein is sett a Nativity to all States in the world.</item>
               <item>7. A Missive to <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Juda.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. The key of Wisdome.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>These following Bookes are not yet given out to be Prined.</head>
               <item>1. <hi>SAbathum Domini;</hi> or the Mystery of the Saboth of God.</item>
               <item>2. The Glory of the Messias on the 110<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Psalme; an expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:118009:34"/>
               <item>3. A Testimony of the Eternall Gospel of the kingdome of God, with 12 marks or signes of Christs Comming.</item>
               <item>4. A Speech of the Lamb of God in three parts.</item>
               <item>5. Information and Instruction unto knowledge.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>Theologia Sanctuum;</hi> The Divinity of Saints.</item>
               <item>7. <hi>Metamorphosis,</hi> or the Perverse of the World.</item>
               <item>8. A treatise of Predestination on <hi>Rom:</hi> the 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg>.</item>
               <item>9. <hi>Mysterium Mediatoris,</hi> The Mystery of the Mediator betwixt God and Man.</item>
               <item>10. <hi>Antilogia Theologica,</hi> the Manifesto of beleife and unbeleife.</item>
               <item>11. <hi>Mysterium Sapientiae,</hi> a Revelation of the Divine Majestie.</item>
               <item>12. <hi>Abissus Sapientiae,</hi> The Revelation of the Depth of God.</item>
               <item>13. A Treatise called Religion.</item>
               <item>14 Revelation of Antichrist.</item>
               <item>15. The little <hi>Nosce teipsum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16. Simple Christendome.</item>
               <item>17. A Too bold Postill on the Gospel appoynted for Sundayes.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Controversies.</head>
               <item>1. An answer to the 15 Motives of the Clergie in <hi>Lubecke, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burrow</hi> and <hi>Lunenburrow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. An Apologeticall answer to <hi>William Christopher Heimius,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The band of Grace.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Mystery of Iniquity,</hi> wherein is examined and refuted the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Osterod,</hi> a Socinian, and the Catechisme of <hi>Rakow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. A discourse against the blasphemous doctrines of the <hi>Photini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. An Examen of the <hi>Photinians,</hi> the markes of false teachers.</item>
               <item>6. The <hi>Photinian</hi> Touchstone, for an answer to <hi>Photinians Florian Crusius,</hi> a Doctor in Physicke.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>There are these Writings of his also.</head>
               <item>1. Upon <hi>Genesis</hi> of 30 sheets in Latine, of the Creation till to the fourth day.</item>
               <item>2. Severall Treatises of Alchymy in the German and Latine Tongue.</item>
               <item>3. A Singular writing on the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:118009:35"/>
               <head>If God permit the Authour intends to write.</head>
               <item>The Mystery of the Immortall Soule.</item>
               <item>Of Regeneration.</item>
               <item>A New Chronology or Computation of the yeares of the world.</item>
               <item>A Continuation on the first Chapter of <hi>Genesis.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118009:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>